<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The arguments upon the writ of habeas corpus, in the Court of Kings Bench. Wherein, are learnedly discussed, not onely the severall branches of the said writ, but also many authorities as well of the common as statute law: and divers ancient and obscure records most amply and elaborately debated and cleared. Together, with the opinion of the court thereupon. Whereunto is annexed, the petition of Sir Iohn Elliot Knight, in behalf of the liberty of the subject.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3649</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E543_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204808</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864270</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864270</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75552)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E543[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The arguments upon the writ of habeas corpus, in the Court of Kings Bench. Wherein, are learnedly discussed, not onely the severall branches of the said writ, but also many authorities as well of the common as statute law: and divers ancient and obscure records most amply and elaborately debated and cleared. Together, with the opinion of the court thereupon. Whereunto is annexed, the petition of Sir Iohn Elliot Knight, in behalf of the liberty of the subject.</title>
                  <author>Eliot, John, Sir, 1592-1632.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Court of King's Bench.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.F. for W. Lee, M. Walbancke, D. Pakeman, and G. Bedell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Includes a petition by Sir John Eliot.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 13 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Habeas corpus --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116495:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116495:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ARGVMENTS UPON THE WRIT OF Habeas Corpus, IN THE COURT OF
KINGS BENCH. WHEREIN, Are learnedly diſcuſſed, not onely the ſeverall
Branches of the ſaid Writ, but alſo many Authorities as well of the Common
as Statute Law: and divers ancient and obſcure Records moſt amply and
ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borately debated and cleared. TOGETHER, With the Opinion of the Court
thereupon. Whereunto is annexed, The Petition of Sir <hi>Iohn Elliot</hi>
Knight, in behalf of the Liberty of the Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>W. Lee, M.
Walbancke, D. Pakeman,</hi> and <hi>G. Bedell.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:116495:2"/> 
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116495:2"/>ARGUMENTS upon the <hi>Habeas
Corpus</hi> concerning Loans.</head>
         <div type="section">
            <head>Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell</hi> his Caſe, <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elis</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               <hi>Caroli, Banco Regis.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR <hi>Thomas Darnell</hi> Baronet, being impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned in the
Fleet by vertue of a warrant ſigned by the Kings Atturney Generall upon the
third of <hi>November,</hi> by Sergeant <hi>Bramſton</hi> his aſſigned
Councell, moved the Juſtices of the Kings Bench to grant him a Writ of
<hi>Habeas Corpus cum cauſa</hi> directed to the Warden of the Fleet to
ſhew that Court the cauſe of his impriſonment, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they might
determine whether his reſtraint were legall or illegall, and it was granted
by the Court returnable <hi>Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> following the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of
<hi>November.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On Thurſday Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell</hi> expected that his Writ
ſhould be returned, but it was delaied, and it was moved that the return
ſhould be on Saturday the tenth of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> which made Sir
<hi>Thomas Darnell</hi> the more remiſſe in ſuing out an <hi>Alias</hi>
upon his <hi>Habeas corpus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On Saturday the Writ was not returned, and thereupon the Kings
Atturney Generall gave order for an <hi>Alias</hi> upon the <hi>Habeas
corpus</hi> for Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell,</hi> returnable upon Thurſday morning
the thirteenth of November; by vertue of which Writ the Warden of the Fleet
brings Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell</hi> to the Kings Bench and returneth as
followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116495:3"/> 
               <hi>Executio iſtius brevis patet in quadem
ſchedula annexat' huic brevi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Return was this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ego Henricus Liloe Miles gardianus priſone Domini Regis de
le</hi> Fleet, <hi>Sereniſsimo domino Regi certifico quod dict'</hi> Thomas
Darnell <hi>Baronet detentus eſt in priſona praedict' ſub cuſtodia mea
virtute cujuſdam Warranti duorum de privato Conſilio mihi directi, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus
tenor ſequitur in his verbis: viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas heretofore the body of Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell</hi> hath been
committed to your cuſtody, theſe are to require you ſtill to continue
him; and to let you know that he was and is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the ſpeciall
command of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et haec eſt cauſa detentionis predict'</hi> Thomae
Darnell.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sergeant <hi>Bramſton.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip, I did not expect this Cauſe at
this time, neither did I hear of it untill I came now into the Hall; and
therefore I ſhall now humbly ſhew you what my Client hath informed me
ſince my comming hither. I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by him that he expected not his
comming to this place to day, the writ by which he was brought hither was not
moved for by him, but was procured without his privity, and ſeeing his caſe
is ſo, and that he perceives the cauſe of his comming, which before he knew
not, his motion to your Lordſhip is, that you would be pleaſed to let him
have the Copy of the return and give him time to ſpeak unto it, and 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116495:3"/> that this writ being not ſent out by his procurement may
not be field.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Heath</hi> Attorney Generall.</speaker>
               <p>My Lords, it is true that this Gent. Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell</hi>
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impriſoned in the <hi>Fleet,</hi> did heretofore move your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
for a <hi>Habeas Corpus, &amp;c.</hi> and it was granted him, and his Majeſty
being made acquainted therewith was very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that he and all his people
might have equall Juſtice, and when they deſire that which ſeemes to
accord with the rules of the Law they ſhould have it. But it fell out ſo
that on the day when the writ ſhould have been returned, the Warden of the
<hi>Fleet</hi> did not return it as it was his duty to have done; he did
forbear to do it upon a commandement, becauſe it was conceived, there being
five at that time to appear, the Court would have been ſtraitned for want of
time, but I imagined that theſe gentlemen who did deſire the writ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
ſhould have again been earneſt to renew them, which it ſeemes they did
not. This <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> was ſent out by ſpeciall command,
becauſe theſe gent. gave out in ſpeeches, and in particular this gent.
That they did wonder why they ſhould be hindred from triall, and what
ſhould be the reaſon their writs were not returned: nay his Majeſty did
tell me that they reported that the King did deny them the courſe of
Juſtice, and therefore hee commanded me to renew the writ, which I did, and
think I may doe it <hi>ex officio.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My Lords, I knew not untill now but that I was committed by Mr.
Atturneys warrant only, and thereupon I did deſire a <hi>Habeas corpus</hi>
at the Barre, which you were pleaſed to grant me, but now I underſtand that
my reſtraint is by another means, and therefore I ſhall crave leave to have
ſome time to ſpeak to it. And as for the words alledged againſt me as if
I had ſpoken them, I humbly. pray they may be no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to my
cauſe, for I do patiently referre my ſelf to your grave cenſures, as
being accuſed of a fact whereof I am no ways guilty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116495:4"/>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Hide</hi> Chiefe Juſtice.</speaker>
               <p>You give a temperate and fair anſwer; and now you may perceive
the upright and ſincere proceedings that have been in this buſineſſe;
you did no ſooner petition to have Councell aſſigned you, but you had it
granted to you, for indeed we cannot deny it, and I know not but that any
Councell might have moved for you, without having been aſſigned for you,
and yet have had no blame, for it is the Kings pleaſure his Lawes ſhould
take place and be executed, and therefore doe wee ſit here: when you made a
motion of the <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> that was likewiſe granted; whether the
commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be by the King or others, this Court is a place where the King doth
ſit in perſon, and we have power to examine it; and if it appears that any
man hath inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or wrong by his impriſonment, we have power to deliver and
diſcharge them, if otherwiſe, he is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by us to priſon
again: now it ſeems you are not ready to ſpeak to this return, if you
deſire further day we ought to grant it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My Lords, I humbly deſire it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chief Juſtice.</speaker>
               <p>I know no cauſe why it ſhould be denied.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sergeant <hi>Bramſton.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My Lords, we ſhall deſire the writ may not be filed, and that
we may have a Copy of the return.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Atturney Generall.</speaker>
               <p>You cannot deny the filing of the writ, if you deſire to have a
Copy of the return.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116495:4"/>
               <speaker>Chief Juſtice.</speaker>
               <p>Although you be remanded at this time to priſon, becauſe you
are not ready to ſpeak to the return, we can adjorn you to a new day upon the
Writ, and ſo you may prepare your ſelf; but if you will not have this
fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, there muſt go out a new <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon muſt
be another return.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sergeant <hi>Bramſton.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My Lord, we deſire ſome time that we may be adviſed whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
we may proceed or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hide.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Will you ſubmit your ſelf to the King?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My Lord, I deſire ſome time to adviſe of my proceedings, I
have moved many men, and offered to retain them of my Councell, but they
refuſe me, and I can get none to be of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell with me without your
aſſiſtance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chief Juſtice.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhall have what Councell aſſigned you, you will have or
deſire, for no offence will be taken againſt any man, that ſhall adviſe
you in your proceedings in Law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Atturney Generall.</speaker>
               <p>I will paſſe my word, they that do adviſe you ſhall have
no offence taken againſt them for it; and I ſhall give my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any
way that you ſhall deſire, either that it may be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or that it may not
be filed; for if you deſire Juſtice you ſhall have it, and the King will
not deny it: but if it ſhall be conceived as it is rumored, that there was a
deniall of Juſtice on the Kings part, you muſt know that his Majeſty is
very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of that. And for the Gent. now he is brought hither, I conceive,
but yet I leave it to your Lordſhips judgement, that <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116495:5"/> the
writ muſt be filed, and you muſt either deliver him or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him, or
elſe it will be an eſcape in the Warden of the <hi>Fleet.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I would not have it thought that I ſhould ſpeak any thing
againſt my <hi>Prince,</hi> and for thoſe words I doe deny them, for upon
my conſcience they never came into my thought, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you ſhall find that
they have been ſpoken by ſome other, but not by any of us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chief Juſtice <hi>Hide.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Sir, you have made a fair anſwer, and I doubt not but Mr.
Attorney will make the like relation of it; you move for the not filing of the
Writ, if you refuſe to have it filed whereby it ſhould not be of Record,
you muſt have no Copy of it, but if you will have it filed, you ſhall have
a Copy of it, and further time to ſpeak to it, chooſe whether of them you
will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sergeant <hi>Bramſton.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>We deſire to have the return read once more: and it was read as
before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sergeant <hi>Bramſton.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>So as the writ may not be filed we will deſire no copy of the
return.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chief Juſtice <hi>Hide.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Then the Gent. muſt return back again into the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody of the
Warden of the <hi>Fleet,</hi> and therefore I ask you whether you deſire to
come hither again upon this Writ, or will you have a new one?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I deſire your Lordſhip that I may have time to conſider of
it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chief Juſtice <hi>Hide.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Then on Gods name take your own time to think of it.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116495:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Michaelis</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Caroli Regis. Thurſday,</hi> 22
<hi>November.</hi> Sir <hi>John Corbet</hi> Baronet, Sir <hi>Walter Earle,</hi>
Sir <hi>John Henningham,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Hampden,</hi> Knights, were
brought to the Barre.</head>
            <div type="subsection">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sergeant <hi>Bramſton.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>MAy it pleaſe your Lordſhip to hear the return read, or
ſhall I open it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chief Juſtice <hi>Hide.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Let it be read.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Keeling</hi> read the return, being the ſame as that of
Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <p>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip, I ſhall humbly move upon this
return in the behalf of Sir <hi>John Henningham</hi> with whom I am of
Councell; it is his petition that he may be bailed from his impriſonment, it
was but in vain for me to move that to a Court of Law which by Law cannot be
granted: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in that regard, that upon this return it will be
queſtioned whether as this return is made, the Gent. may be bailed or not; I
ſhall humbly offer up to your Lordſhip the caſe, and ſome reaſons out
of mine underſtanding, ariſing out of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn it ſelf, to ſatisfie
your Lordſhip that theſe Priſoners may, and as their caſe is, ought to
be bailed by your Lordſhip.</p>
                  <p>The exception that I take to this return, is as well to the
matter and ſubſtance of the return, as to the manner and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall form
thereof; the exceptions that I take to the matter is in ſeverall
reſpects.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116495:6"/> That the return is too generall, there is no
ſufficient cauſe ſhewn in ſpeciall or in generall of the commitment of
this Gentleman; and as it is inſufficient for the cauſe, ſo alſo in the
time of the firſt impriſonment, for howſoever here doth appear a time
upon the ſecond warrant from the Lords of the Councell to detain him ſtill
in priſon, yet by the return no time can appear when he was firſt
impriſoned, though it be neceſſary it ſhould be ſhewn, and if that
time appear not, there is no cauſe your Lordſhip ſhould remand him, and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently he is to be delivered.</p>
                  <p>Touching the matter of the return, which is the cauſe of his
impriſonment, it is expreſſed to be <hi>Per ſpeciale mandatum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini
Regis:</hi> This is too generall and uncertain, for that it is not manifeſt
what kind of command this was.</p>
                  <p>Touching the legall form of the return, it is not as it ought to
be fully and poſitively the return of the Keeper himſelf on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but it
comes with a <hi>ſignificavit</hi> or <hi>prout</hi> that he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<hi>Per ſpeciale mandatum domini Regis,</hi> as appeareth by warrant from the
Lords of the Councell, not of the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that is not good in
legall form.</p>
                  <p>For the matter and ſubſtance of the return it is not good,
becauſe there ought to be a cauſe of that impriſonment.</p>
                  <p>This writ is the means, and the only means that the Subject hath
in this and ſuch like caſe to obtain his liberty; there are other writs by
which men are delivered from reſtraint, as that <hi>de homine
replegiando,</hi> but extends not to this cauſe, for it is particularly
excepted in the body of the writ <hi>de manucaptione et de cautione
admittenda,</hi> but they lie in other caſes; but the writ of <hi>Habeas
corpus</hi> is the only means the ſubject hath to obtain his liberty, and the
end of this writ is to return the cauſe of the impriſonment, that it may be
examined in this Court, whether the parties ought to be diſcharged or not,
but that cannot be done upon this return, for the cauſe of the 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116495:6"/> impriſonment of this Gentleman at firſt is ſo far from
appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring particularly by it, that there is no cauſe at all expreſſed in
it.</p>
                  <p>This writ requires that the cauſe of the impriſonment
ſhould be returned, and if the cauſe be not ſpecially certified by it,
yet ſhould it at the laſt be ſhewn in generall, that it may appear to the
Judges of the Court, and it muſt be expreſſed ſo farre as that it may
appear to be none of thoſe cauſes for which by the Law of the Kingdome the
Subject ought not to be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and it ought to be expreſſed that it
was by preſentment or indictment, and not upon petition or ſuggeſtion
made to the King and Lords, which is againſt the ſtatute made in the 25
<hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. 42 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>By the ſtatute 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. It is
ordained and eſtabliſhed, that no man from henceforth ſhall be taken by
petition or ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion made to the King or his Councell, but by indictment
or courſe of Law; and accordingly it was enacted, 42 <hi>E.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. the title of
which ſtatute is, None ſhall be put to anſwer an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation made to
the King without preſentment. Then my Lord, it being ſo, although the
cauſe ſhould not need to be expreſſed in ſuch manner as that it may
appear to be none of theſe cauſes mentioned in the ſtatute, or elſe the
Subject by this return loſeth the benefit and advantage of theſe Laws,
which be their birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and inheritance; but in this return there is no
cauſe at all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of the firſt commitment, and therefore it is plain
that there is no cauſe for your Lordſhip to remand him: but there is
cauſe you ſhould deliver him, ſince the writ is to bring the body and the
cauſe of the impriſonment before your Lordſhip.</p>
                  <p>But it may be objected, that this writ of <hi>Habeas corpus</hi>
doth not demand the cauſe of the firſt commitment, but of the detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
onely; and ſo the writ is ſatisfied by the return, for though it ſhew no
cauſe of the firſt commitment, but of detaining on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet it declareth a
cauſe why the Gentleman is detained in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; this is no anſwer, nor
can give any ſatisfaction, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the cauſe is to be
returned is for the Subjects liberty, that if it ſhall appear a good and
ſufficient cauſe to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <pb n="10" facs="tcp:116495:7"/> then to be
remanded; if your Lordſhip think and finde it inſufficient, hee is to bee
enlarged.</p>
                  <p>This is the end of this writ, and this cannot appeare to your
Lordſhip, unleſſe the time of the firſt commitment be expreſſed in
the return. I know that in ſome caſes the time is not mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, as when
the cauſe of the commitment is (and that ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially) returned, as
that the time is not materiall, it is enough to ſhew the cauſe without the
time as after a conviction or triall had by Law; But when it is in this manner,
that the time is the matter it ſelf: for intend what cauſe you will of the
commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yea though for the higheſt cauſe of treaſon, there is no
doubt but that upon the return thereof the time of it muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; for it
being before triall and conviction had by Law, it is but an accuſation, and
he that is onely accuſed, and the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation ought by Law to be let to
bail.</p>
                  <p>But I beſeech your Lordſhip to obſerve the conſequence
of this Cauſe. If the Law be, that upon this return this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould
be remanded, I will not diſpute whether or no, a man may be impriſoned
before he be convicted according to the Law: but if this return ſhall be
good, then his impriſonment ſhall not continue on for a time, but for ever;
and the Subjects of this Kingdome may be reſtrained of their liberties
perpetually, and by Law there can be no remedy for the Subject; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
this return cannot ſtand with the Laws of the Realm, or that of <hi>Magna
Carta.</hi> Nor with the ſtatute of 28 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 3. for if
a man be not baileable upon this return, they cannot have the benefit of
theſe two Laws, which are the inheritance of the Subject.</p>
                  <p>If your Lordſhip ſhall think this to be a ſufficient
cauſe, then it goeth to a perpetuall impriſonment of the Subject: for in
all thoſe cauſes which may concern the Kings Subjects, and are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable
to all times and caſes, we are not to reflect upon the preſent time and
government, where juſtice and mercy floweth, but we are to look what may
betide us in the time to come, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
                  <p>It muſt be agreed on all ſides, that the time of the firſt
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116495:7"/> doth not appear in this return; but by a latter
warrant from the Lords of the Councell, there is a time indeed expreſſed
for the continuing of him in priſon, and that appears; but if this ſhall be
a good cauſe to remand theſe Gentlemen to priſon, they may lie there this
ſeven years longer, and ſeven years after them, nay all the days of their
lives. And if they ſue out a writ of <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> it is but making
a new warrant, and they ſhall be remanded, and ſhall never have the
advantage of the Laws which are the beſt inheritance of every Subject.</p>
                  <p>And in <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>xfol.</hi> 36. the Laws are called
the great inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of every Subject, and the inheritance of inheritances,
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which inheritance we have no inheritance.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are the exceptions I deſire to offer up to your
Lordſhip, touching the return, for the inſufficiency of the cauſe
returned, and the defect of the time of the firſt commitment, which ſhould
have been expreſſed.</p>
                  <p>I will not labour in objections till they be made againſt me,
in regard the ſtatute of <hi>Weſtminſter primo</hi> is ſo frequent in
every mans mouth, that at the Common Law thoſe men that were committed in
four caſes were not repleviſable <hi>(viz.)</hi> thoſe that were taken
for the death of a man, or the commandment of the King, or his Juſtices for
the foreſt; I ſhall ſpeak ſomething to it, though I intend not to
ſpend much time about it, for it tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth not this Caſe we have in
queſtion.</p>
                  <p>For that is concerning a Caſe of the Common Law, when men are
taken by the Kings writs, and not by word of mouth, and it ſhall be ſo
expounded, as Maſter <hi>Stamford fol.</hi> 73. yet it is nothing to this
Caſe, for if you will take the true meaning of that ſtatute, it extends not
at all to this writ of <hi>Habeas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus;</hi> for the words are plain, they
ſhall be repleviſable by the Common writ, that is, by the writ <hi>de
homine replegiando,</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Sheriffe to deliver them if they were
baileable, but this Caſe is above the Sheriffe, and he is not to be Judge in
it, <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116495:8"/> whether the cauſe of the commitment be ſufficient
or not, as it appears in <hi>Fitz Herbert, de homine replegiando,</hi> and many
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, and not of the very words of the ſtatute, this is clear, for
thereby many other cauſes mentioned, as the death of a man, the commandment
of the Juſtices, &amp;c. In which the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute ſaith, men are not
repleviſable; but will a man conceive that the meaning is, that they ſhall
not be bailed at all, but live in perpetuall impriſonment? I think I ſhall
not need to ſpend time, in that it is ſo plain, let me but make one
inſtance.</p>
                  <p>A man is taken <hi>de morte hominis,</hi> he is not baileable by
writ, ſaith this ſtatute, that is, by the common writ, there was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
writ for this Caſe, and that was called <hi>de odio &amp; acia,</hi> as
appeareth. <hi>Bracton Coron.</hi> 34. this is the writ intended by the
ſtatute, which is a common writ, and not a ſpeciall writ; But my Lord as
this writ <hi>de odio &amp; acia</hi> was before this ſtatute, ſo it was
afterwards taken away by the ſtatute of 28 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.
But before that ſtatute, this writ did lie in the ſpeciall Caſe as is
ſhewn in <hi>Brooks</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Reports, <hi>Powlters</hi> Caſe, and the end
of this writ was, that the Subject might not be too long detained in priſon,
as till the Juſtices of <hi>Eyre</hi> diſcharged them, ſo that the Law
intended not that a man ſhould ſuffer perpetuall impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, for they
were very carefull that men ſhould not bee kept too long in priſon, which
is alſo a Liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and my Lord that this Court hath bailed
upon a ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of high treaſon, I will offer it to your Lordſhip,
when I ſhall ſhew you preſidents in theſe caſes of a commitment by
the Privy Councell, or by the King himſelf: But before I offer theſe
preſidents unto your Lordſhip, of which there be many, I ſhall by your
Lordſhips favour ſpeak a little to the next exception, and that is to the
matter of the return, which I finde to be <hi>per ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciale mandatum domini
Regis</hi> 8. and what is, that it is by this writ there may be ſundry
commands by the King, we finde a ſpeciall command often in our Books, as in
the ſtatute of <hi>Marl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough cap.</hi> 8. they were impriſoned.
<hi>Rediſſ.</hi> ſhall not be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered without the ſpeciall command
of our Lord the King, and ſo in <hi>Bracton, De Actionibus,</hi> the laſt
chapter, where it appears <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116495:8"/> that the King commandment for
impriſonments is by ſpeciall writ, ſo by writ again men are to be
delivered, for in the caſe of <hi>Rediſs'</hi> or <hi>Poſt
Rediſs',</hi> if it ſhall be removed by a <hi>Certiorare,</hi> is by a
ſpeciall writ to deliver parties: ſo that by this appears that by the Kings
commandment to impriſon, and to deliver in thoſe caſes, is underſtood
this writ, and ſo it may be in this caſe which wee have heard.</p>
                  <p>And this return here is a ſpeciall <hi>Mandatum,</hi> it may
bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to be under ſome of the Kings Seals, 42 <hi>Aſſ.</hi>
and ought to be delivered, and will you make a difference betweene the Kings
command under his ſeal, and his command by word of mouth; what difference
there is, I leave it to your Lordſhips judgement, but if there be any, it is
the more materiall that it ſhould be expreſſed what manner of command it
was, which doth not here appear; and therefore it may be the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand by
writ, or his command under his ſeal, or his command by word of mouth
alone.</p>
                  <p>And if of an higher nature, there is none of theſe commands,
then the other, doubtleſſe, it is that by writ, or under ſeal, for they
are of record, and in theſe the perſon may be bailed, and why not in this?
As to the legall forme, admitting there were ſubſtances in the return, yet
there wants legall form, for the writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> is the
commandment of the King to the Keeper of the priſons, and thereupon they are
to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn both of the body, and of the cauſe of the commitment, and
that cauſe is to appear of them who are the immediate Officers. And if he
doth it by ſignification from another, that returne is defective in Law, and
therefore this return cannot be good, for it muſt be from the Officer
himſelf, and if the cauſe returned by him be good, it bindes the
priſoners.</p>
                  <p>The warrant of the Lords was but a direction for him, he might
have made his return to have been expreſly by the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, there
was warrant for it, I ſhall not need to put you caſes of it, for it is not
enough that he returns that he was certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <pb n="41" facs="tcp:116495:9"/> that the
commitment was by the Kings command, but he muſt of himſelf return this
fact as it was done. And now my Lord I ſhal offer to your Lordſhip
preſidents of divers kindes, upon commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by the Lords of the Privy
Councell, upon commitments by the ſpeciall command of the King, and upon
commitments both by the King and the Lords together. And howſoever I
conceive, which I ſubmit to your Lordſhip, that our caſe will not ſtand
upon preſidents, but upon the fundamentall Laws and Statutes of this Realm,
and though the preſidents look the one way or the other, they are to be
brought back unto the Lawes by which the Kingdome is governed. In the firſt
of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 9. one <hi>Hariſon</hi> was
committed to the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalſey</hi> by the command of the King, and being
removed by <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus</hi> into the Court, the cauſe returned was,
that he was committed <hi>per mandatum Domini Regis,</hi> and he was
bailed.</p>
                  <p>In the fortieth of <hi>Elizabeth, Thomas Wendon</hi> was
commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Gatehouſe by the commandment of the Queen, and Lords of the
Councell, and being removed by an <hi>Habeas Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> upon the generall
return, and he was bailed.</p>
                  <p>In 8 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> one <hi>Caeſar</hi> was committed by the
Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and this being returned upon his <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi>
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the examination of this caſe it doth appear that it was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled,
that the return ſhould be amended, or elſe the priſoner ſhould be
delivered.</p>
                  <p>The preſidents concerning the commitment by the Lords of the
Councel, are in effect the ſame with theſe, where the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment is, by
the reaſon why the cauſe of the commitment ſhould not be ſhewn, holds
in both caſes, and that is the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of ſuit, and therefore
Maſter <hi>Stamford</hi> makes the command of the King, and that of the Lords
of the Privy Councell, to be both as one; and to this purpoſe, if they
ſpeak, he ſpeaks, and if he ſpeaks, they ſpeak.</p>
                  <p>The preſidents that we can ſhew you, how the Subject hath 
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116495:9"/> been delivered upon commitment by the Lords of the Councel,
as in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, as in the times of Queen
<hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> are infinite: as in the ninth of
<hi>Elizabeth; Thomas Lawrence</hi> was committed to the Towre by the Lords of
the Councell, and bailed upon an <hi>Habeas Corpus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the 43 of <hi>Elizabeth, Calvins</hi> caſe.</p>
                  <p>In the third of <hi>Elizabeth, Vernons</hi> caſe.</p>
                  <p>Theſe were committed for high treaſon, and yet bailed, for
in all theſe caſes there muſt be a conviction in due time, or a
delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance by Law.</p>
                  <p>There be divers other preſidents that might be ſhewn to your
Lordſhip. In 12 <hi>Iacobi, Miles Renards.</hi> In 12 <hi>Jacobi, Rot.</hi>
155. <hi>Richard Beckwiths</hi> caſe. In 4 <hi>Iacobi,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas
Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> was committed for treaſon to the Towre of <hi>London,</hi> and
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards was brought hither, and bailed, and ſince our caſe ſtands
upon this return, and yet there is no ſufficient cauſe in Law expreſſed
in the return of the detaining this Gentleman; and ſince theſe preſidents
doe warrant our proceedings, my humble ſuit unto this Court is, that the
Gentleman Sir <hi>Iohn Henningham,</hi> who hath petitioned his Majeſty, that
he may have the benefit of the Law, and his Majeſty hath ſignified it, It
is his pleaſure that juſtice according to the Law ſhould be adminiſtred
at all times in generall to all his Subjects, and particularly to theſe
Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, which is their birth-right: My humble ſuit to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
is, that theſe Gentlemen may have the benefit of that Law, and be delivered
from their impriſonment.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Maſter <hi>Noye</hi> his Argument, of Councell with Sir
<hi>Walter Earl</hi> at that time.</head>
               <sp>
                  <p>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip, I am of Councell with Sir
<hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Earl,</hi> one of the priſoners at the Barre; the return of this
writ is as thoſe that have been before, they are much of one te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116495:10"/> and as you have heard the tenour of that, ſo this Gent.
coming hither by an <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> I will by your Lordſhips fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
read the writ.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Carolus Dei Gratia &amp;c. Iohanni Lylo Milit' Guardian'
Priſon' noſtrae de le Fleet Salut', Praecipimus tibi quod corpus</hi>
Walteri Earl <hi>Milit' in priſon' noſtra ſub cuſtodia tua detent' ut
dicit una cum cauſa deten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis ſuae quocunque nomine praedict'</hi>
Walter' <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat in eadem Habeas Corpus ad ſubjiciendum &amp;
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiendum ea quae curia noſtra de eo ad tunc &amp; ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ordin' conting'
in hac parte &amp; haec nullatenus omit' periculo incumbent' &amp; habeas tibi
hoc breve, Teſt'</hi> Hyde, <hi>apud Weſtminſter quarto die Novembris,
Anno</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Executio iſtius brevis patet in quadam ſchedula huic
brevi annexat'</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Priſonum Regis de le
Fleet.</note>Reſponſ. Johan' Liloe Guardian' Priſon' de le Fleet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ego Iohannes Lyloe Mil' Guardian' Priſon' domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Regis de
le Fleet, Sereniſsimo Domino Regi, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Weſtminſter'</hi> 8. <hi>Poſt
receptionem hujus brevis quod in hac ſchedula eſt mentionat', Certifico
quod</hi> Walter Earl <hi>miles, in eodem brevium nominat' de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentus eſt in
Priſona de le Fleet ſub cuſtodia mea praedict' per ſpeciale mandatum
domini Regis mihi <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116495:10"/> ſignificatum per Warrantum duorum
&amp; aliorum de Privato Concilio per Honorabiliſsimi dicti Domini Regis,
cujus quidem tenor ſequitur in haec verba.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereas Sir <hi>Walter Earle</hi> Knight, was heretofore
committed to your cuſtody, theſe are to will and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you ſtill to
detain him, letting you know, that both his firſt commitment, and this
direction for the continuance of him in priſon, were and are by his
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſpeciall commandment, from <hi>White Hall,</hi> 7
<hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vembris,</hi> 1627.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Coventree C. S.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Henry Mancheſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Suffolk.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bridgewater.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kellie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>R. Duneln'.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Edmunds.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Cook.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Marlebrugh.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Pembrook.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Totnes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Grandiſſon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Guliel' Bath &amp; Wells.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Robert Nanton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Richard Weſton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Humphrey Mayes.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the Guardian of the Fleet or his Deputy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Et haec eſt cauſa detentionis praedict'</hi> Walteri
Earl <hi>ſub cuſtodia mea in Priſon' praedict'. Attamen corpus
ejuſdem</hi> Walteri <hi>coram Domino Rege ad diem &amp; locum praedictum,
poſt receptionem brevis praedict' pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat' habeo prout iſtud breve in ſe
exiget &amp; requiret.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116495:11"/> 
                     <hi>Reſpon'</hi> Johan' Liloe <hi>milit'
Guardian Priſon de le Fleet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Lord, the firſt <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> bears date the 4 of
<hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> then there is an <hi>Alias habeas</hi> bears
<hi>Teſte</hi> after that, and the tenour thereof is a command to the Warden
of the Fleet, <hi>quod habeas corpus</hi> Walteri Earle <hi>coram nobis ad
ſubjiciendum &amp; recipiendum ea quae curia noſtra de eo &amp;c. ordin'
conting.</hi> And the Warden of the Fleet he certifies as your Lordſhip have
heard; May it pleaſe your Lordſhip, I deſire as before was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired for
the other Gentlemen, that Sir <hi>Walter Earl</hi> may bee alſo bailed, if
there be no other cauſe of his impriſonment: for if there were a cauſe
certified, and that cauſe were not ſufficient to detain him ſtill in
priſon, your Lordſhip would baile him, and if a man ſhould bee in worſe
caſe, when there is no cauſe certified at all, that was very hard.</p>
                  <p>The writ is, that he ſhould bring the priſoner <hi>coram
nobis</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, the end of that is <hi>ad ſubjiciendum &amp;
recipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum;</hi> now I conceive that though there be a ſignification of the
Kings pleaſure to have this Gentleman impriſoned, yet when the King grants
this writ to bring the priſoner hither, <hi>ad ſubjicien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum &amp;
recipiendum,</hi> his pleaſure likewiſe is to have the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner let goe,
if by Law he be not chargeable, or otherwiſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him ſtill in
priſon, if the caſe ſo require it.</p>
                  <p>I will put your Lordſhip in minde of a caſe, and it was
<hi>Paſch.</hi> 9 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>M.</hi> 3. I will cite by the
<hi>placita,</hi> becauſe my Book is not paged as other Books are, it is in
the caſe of a <hi>Ceſſavit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In that caſe there were two things conſiderable, the one
that there was a ſignification of the Kings pleaſure paſt, and that
determined with him: the other, that though there was a ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the
Kings pleaſure, before which was, yet there comes after that a writ, and that
was another ſignification of the Kings pleaſure, that the priſoner ſhal
be brought hither <hi>ad ſubjiciendum,</hi> to ſubmit himſelf to
puniſhment, if he have deſerved it, or <hi>ad <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116495:11"/>
recipiendum,</hi> to receive his enlargement, and be delivered, if there be no
cauſe of his impriſonment.</p>
                  <p>And if upon an <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> a cauſe of commitment
bee certified, that cauſe is to be tried here before your Lordſhip. But if
no cauſe be ſhewn, then the proceedings muſt be <hi>ut curia noſtra ad
mar' contigerit,</hi> the Court muſt doe that which ſtands with Law and
Juſtice, and that is to deliver him.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, I ſhall be bold to move one word more touching this
return: I conceive that every Officer to a Court of Juſtice muſt make his
return of his own act, or of the act of another, and not what he is certified
of by another.</p>
                  <p>But in this caſe the Warden of the Fleet doth not certifie
himſelf, of himſelfe, that this Gentleman was commanded to him by the King,
but that he was certified by the Lords of the Councell, that it was the Kings
pleaſure that he ſhould detain him. But in our caſe the Warden of the
Fleet muſt certifie the immediate cauſe, and not the cauſe of the
cauſe, as it doth by this return, <hi>Detentus eſt ſub cuſtodia mea per
ſpeciale manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Domini Regis mihi ſignificatum per Warrantum duorum de
Privato Concilio;</hi> that is not the uſe in Law, but he ought to return the
primary cauſe, and not the ſubſequent cauſe, as in 32 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.
returne, <hi>Rex vicecom'</hi> 87. in a writ <hi>De homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne replegiando,</hi>
againſt an Abbot, the Sheriffe returns, that hee hath ſent to the Bayliffe
of the Abbot, and he anſwered him that the party was the Abbots villain, and
ſo he cannot deliver him, that is held an inſufficient return, and a new
<hi>Alias</hi> was granted, but if the Sheriffe had returned, that the Abbot
did certifie him ſo, it had been good, but he muſt not return what is
certified him by another.</p>
                  <p>In one of the preſidents that hath been noted, as that of
<hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> 22 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. there the Guardian of the priſon
certifies that <hi>Parker detentus eſt ſub cuſtodia mea per mandatum
Domini Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis mihi nunciatum per Robertum Pecke;</hi> now our caſe is by the
Nunciation of many, but in Law <hi>majus &amp; minus non va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riant 
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116495:12"/> in ſpetione,</hi> the certification of one and of many
is of the ſame effect, although in morall underſtanding there may bee a
difference.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Trin.</hi> 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 46. in this Court
in 21 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Book there is a peece of it: The Abbot of
<hi>Burey</hi> brings a prohibition out of this Court, the Biſhop of
<hi>Norwich</hi> pleadeth in Bar of that <hi>Quod mihi teſtificatum, quod
continetur in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chivis,</hi> that he is excommunicated; there were two
exceptions taken to this caſe in this preſident, and they are both in one
caſe, the firſt was, that no caſe appeareth, why he was excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated:
there may be cauſes why he ſhould be excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and then he ſhould
be barred, and there may be cauſes why the excommunication ſhould not barre
him: for it may be the excommunication was for bringing the action, which was
the Kings writ, and therefore becauſe there was no cauſe of the
excommunication returned, it was ruled that it was not good. The other reaſon
is that upon the Roll, which is <hi>mihi teſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now every man when he will make a Certificate to the Court,
<hi>Proprium factum ſuum non alterius ſignificare debet,</hi> he muſt
inform the Court of the immediate act done, and not that ſuch things are told
him, or that ſuch things are ſignified unto him, but that was not done in
this caſe, and therefore it was held in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient: and ſo in this caſe
of ours, I conceive the return is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient in the form, there is another
cauſe my Lord, for which I conceive this return is not good.</p>
                  <p>But firſt I will be bold to inform your Lordſhip touching
the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> 29. <hi>Nullus liber homo capiatur vel
impriſonetur &amp;c. nec ſuper eum mittimus niſi per legale judicium
parium ſuorum vel per legem terrae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That in this Statute theſe words <hi>in Carcerem</hi> are
omitted out of the printed Books: for it ſhould be <hi>nec eum in Carcerem
mittimus.</hi> For theſe words <hi>per legem terrae;</hi> what <hi>Lex
terrae</hi> ſhould be, I will not take upon me to expound, otherwiſe then I
finde them to be expounded by Acts of Parliament; and this <pb n="21" facs="tcp:116495:12"/>
is that they are underſtood to be the proceſſe of the Law, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
by writ, ſometimes by attachment of the perſon: but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ſpeciale
mandatum Domini Regis</hi> be intended by that or no, I leave it to your
Lordſhips expoſition upon two petitions of the Commons, and anſwer of the
King, in 36 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                     </hi> 9. and <hi>n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                     </hi> 20.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt of them the Commons complain that the great
Charter, the Charter of the Foreſt, and other Statutes were broken, and they
deſire that for the good of himſelfe and of his people, they might be kept
and put in execution, and that they might not be infringed by making an
arreſt by ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or otherwiſe: and the anſwer was, that the
aſſent of the Lords eſtabliſhed and ordained, that the ſaid Charter
and other Statutes ſhould be put in execution according to the petition, and
that is without any diſturbance by arreſt by ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or
otherwiſe, for it was granted, as it was petitioned.</p>
                  <p>In the ſame year, for they were very carefull of this matter,
and it was neceſſary it ſhould be ſo, for it was then an uſuall thing
to take men by writs <hi>quibuſdam de cauſis,</hi> and many of theſe
words cauſed many Acts of Parliament: and it may be ſome of theſe writs
may be ſhewn, and I ſay in the ſame year they complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that men were
impriſoned by ſpeciall command, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out indictment or other legall
courſe of Law, and they deſired that thing may not be done upon men by
ſpeciall command a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the great Charter.</p>
                  <p>The King makes anſwer that he is well pleaſed therewith:
that was the firſt anſwer; and for the future he hath added farther, if any
man be grieved let him complain, and right ſhall be done unto him. This my
Lord is an explanation of the great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as alſo the Statute of 37
<hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 18. is a Commentary up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, that men ſhould
not be committed upon ſuggeſtion made to the King, without due proofs of
Law againſt them, and ſo it is enacted twice in one year.</p>
                  <p>Wee finde more printed Bookes, as in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth,
<hi>Mius de fiacts, Fitz.</hi> 182. which is a ſtrong caſe: under fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour 
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116495:13"/> in an action of Treſpaſſe for cutting down trees:
the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant ſaith, that the place where the trees are cut, is parcell of
the Manor of <hi>B,</hi> whereof the King is ſeiſed in fee, and that the
King did command him to cut them: and the opinion of the Court was, that this
was no good plea, without ſhewing the ſpecialty of the command, and they
ſaid, if the King command me to arreſt a man, and I arreſt him, he
ſhall have an action of falſe impriſonment againſt me, although it were
done in the Kings preſence.</p>
                  <p>In 1 <hi>Ioh. cap.</hi> 7. <hi>fol.</hi> 46. it is in print, and
there we leave it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Huſſey</hi> Chief Juſtice ſaith, that Sir <hi>Iohn
Markham</hi> told King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, that he could not arreſt a
man upon ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of felony or treaſon, as any of his Subjects might,
becauſe if he ſhould wrong a man by ſuch arreſt, the parties could have
no remedy againſt him, if any man ſhall ſtand upon it; here is a
ſignification of the Kings pleaſure, not to have the cauſe of the
commitment examined, he hath here another ſignification of his pleaſure by
writ, whereby the party is brought hither <hi>ad ſubjiciendum &amp;
recipiendum,</hi> that he hath made your Lordſhip Judge of that, that
ſhould be objected againſt this Gentleman, and either to puniſh him, or
to deliver him, and if here be no cauſe ſhewn, it is to be intended that
the party is to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that it is the Kings pleaſure it ſhould
be ſo, and the writ is a ſufficient warrant for the doing of it, there
being no cauſe ſhewn of the impriſonment; and now my Lord, I will ſpeak
a word to the writ of <hi>De homine replegiando,</hi> and no other writ, for
that was the common writ, and the four cauſes expreſſed in that Statute,
to wit, the death of a man, the command of the King, or his Juſtices, or
Foreſt, were excepted in that writ before that Statute made, as appears
<hi>Bracton</hi> 133. ſo that the writ was at the Common Law before that
Statute.</p>
                  <p>And it apppears by our Books, that if a man be brought hither by
an <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> though he were impriſoned <hi>De morte
hominis,</hi> as in the 21 of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, 7.
<hi>Winck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> was bailed here, this Court bailed him, for he was brought
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116495:13"/> hither <hi>ad ſubjiciendum &amp; recipiendum,</hi> and
not to he in priſon God knows how long; and if the Statute ſhould be
expounded otherwiſe, there were no bailing men outlawed or breakers of
priſons, for they are not within this Statute, and yet this Court doth it at
pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>But plainly by the Statute it ſelf, it appears that it meant
only to the common writ, for the preamble recites, that the Sheriffs and other,
have taken and kept in priſon perſons detected of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, and let out to
plevin ſuch as were not repriſable to grieve the one party, and to the gain
of the other; and foraſmuch as before this time it was not determined what
priſoners were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſable, which not, but onely in certain caſes were
expreſſed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ordained, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Now this is no more but for direction of the keepers of the
priſons, for it leaves the matter to the diſcretion of the Judges, whether
bailable or no, not of the Judges, for when the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute hath declared who are
repleviable, who are not, as men out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed have abjured the Realm: Proves
ſuch as be taken in the manner, breakers of priſons, burners of houſes,
makers of falſe money, counterfeiting of the Kings Seal, and the like, it is
then ordained, that if the Sheriffe or any other, let any goe at large by
ſurety, that is not repriſable, if he be Sheriffe, Conſtable, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
other that hath the keeping of priſons, and thereof be attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he ſhall
loſe his office and fee for ever, ſo that it extends to the common Gaolers
and keepers of priſons, to direct them in what caſes they ſhall let men
to bail, and in what caſes not: &amp; that they ſhall not be Judges to whom
to let to replevin, and whom to keep in priſon, but it extends not to the
Judges, for if the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Statute had meant them in it, they ſhould
have put a pain upon them alſo.</p>
                  <p>So then, I conclude upon theſe under your Lordſhips favour,
that as this caſe is, there ſhould have been a cauſe of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment
expreſſed, for theſe Gentlemen are brought hither by writ <hi>ad
ſubjiciendum,</hi> if they be charged, and <hi>ad recipiendum</hi> if 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116495:14"/> they be not charged, and therefore in regard there is no
charge againſt them whereupon they ſhould be detained in priſon any
longer; we deſire that they may be bailed or diſcharged by your
Lordſhip.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Maſter <hi>Seldens</hi> Argument at the Kings Bench Bar the
ſame day.</head>
               <sp>
                  <p>My Lords, I am of Councell with Sir <hi>Edmond Hampden,</hi> his
caſe is the ſame with the other two Gentlemen, I cannot hope to ſay much
after that that hath been ſaid, yet if it ſhall pleaſe your Lordſhip, I
ſhall remember you of ſo much as is befallen my lot: Sir <hi>Edmond
Hampden</hi> is brought hither by a writ of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas corpus,</hi> and the
keeper of the Gatehouſe hath returned upon the writ, that Sir <hi>Edmond
Hampden</hi> is detained in priſon <hi>per ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciale mandatum domini Regis,
mihi ſignificatum per Warr antum duorum Privati Concilii dicti domini
Regis,</hi> and then he recites the warrants of the Lords of the Councel, which
is, that they doe will and require him to detain this Gentleman ſtill in
priſon, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him know that his firſt impriſonment, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip, I ſhall humbly move you that
this Gentleman may alſo be bailed, for under favour my Lord, there is no
cauſe in the return, why he ſhould be any farther im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned and
reſtrained of his liberty.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, I ſhall ſay ſomething to the form of the writ,
and of the return, but very little to them both, becauſe there is a very
little left for me to ſay.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, to the form, I ſay it expreſſeth nothing of the
firſt caption, and therefore it is inſufficient, I will adde one reaſon
as hath been ſaid: the <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> hath onely theſe words,
<hi>quod habeas corpus ejus una cum cauſa detentionis &amp; non
cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis:</hi> But my Lord, becauſe in all impriſonment, there is a
cauſe of caption and detention, the caption is to be anſwered aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as
the detention.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116495:14"/> I have ſeen many writs of this nature,
and on them the caption is returned, that they might ſee the time of the
caption, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by know whether the party ſhould be delivered or no, and
that in regard of the length of his impriſonment.</p>
                  <p>The next exception I took to the form is, that there is much
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty in it, ſo that no man can tell when the writ came to the keeper
of the priſon, whether before the return or after, for it appears not when
the Kings command was, for the commitment or the ſignification of the
Councell came to him: It is true, that it appears that the warrant was dated
the ſeventh of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> but when it came to the keeper of the
priſon that appeares not at all; and therefore as for want of mentioning the
ſame time of the caption, ſo for not expreſſing the ſame time when
this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant came, I think the return is faulty in form and void.</p>
                  <p>And for apparent contradiction alſo, the return is
inſufficient, for in that part of the return which is before the warrant, it
is ſaid <hi>quod detentus eſt per ſpeciale mandatum domini Regis,</hi>
the warrant of the Lords of the Councell; the very ſyllables of that warrant
are, that the Lords of the Councell doe will and require him ſtill to detain
him, which is contrary to the firſt part of the return.</p>
                  <p>Beſides my Lord, the Lords themſelves ſay in another place
and paſſage of the warrant, that the King commanded them to commit him, and
ſo it is their commitment, ſo that upon the whole matter there appears to
be a clear contradiction in the return, and there being a contradiction in the
return, it is void.</p>
                  <p>Now my Lord, I wil ſpeak a word or two to the matter of the
return, and that is touching the impriſonment, <hi>per ſpeciale mandatum
domini Regis,</hi> by the Lords of the Councell without any cauſe
expreſſed, and admitting of any or either of both of theſe to be the
return: I think that by the conſtant and ſettled Laws of this kingdome,
without which we have nothing, no man can be juſtly impriſoned by either of
them, without a cauſe of the commitment expreſſed in the return. My Lord,
in both <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116495:15"/> the laſt Arguments the ſtatutes have been
mentioned and fully expreſſed, yet I will adde a little to that which hath
been ſaid.</p>
                  <p>The ſtatute of <hi>Magna Carta cap.</hi> 29. that ſtatute if
it were fully executed as it ought to be, every man would enjoy his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
better then he doth.</p>
                  <p>The Law ſaith expreſly, no Free-man ſhall be impriſoned
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due proceſſe of the Law; out of the very body of this Act of
Parliament, beſides the explanation of other ſtatutes, it appears,
<hi>Nullus liber homo capiatur vel impriſonetur niſi per legem
ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae.</hi> My Lord, I know theſe words <hi>legem terrae,</hi> doe leave
the queſtion where it was if the interpretation of the Statute were not. But
I think under your Lordſhips favour, there it muſt be intended by due
courſe of Law to be either by preſentment or by indictment.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, if the meaning of theſe words <hi>Per legem
terrae</hi> were but as we uſe to ſay, according to the lawes, which leaves
the matter very uncertain: and <hi>per ſpeciale mandatum, &amp;c.</hi> be
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the meaning of theſe words, according to the law, then this Act had
done nothing. The Act is, No Free-man ſhall be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned but by the law
of the land; if you will underſtand theſe words, <hi>per legem terrae,</hi>
in the firſt ſenſe, this ſtatute ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Villains as well as
to Free-men, for if I impriſon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, Villain, the Villain may have an
action of falſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment. But the Lords and the King (for then they
both had Villains) might impriſon them, and the Villain could have no remedy;
but theſe words in the ſtatute <hi>per legem terrae,</hi> were to the
Free-man, which ought not to be impriſoned, but by due proceſſe of law,
and unleſſe the interpretation ſhall be this, the Free-man ſhall have
no priviledge above the Villain.</p>
                  <p>So that I conceive my Lord, theſe words <hi>per legem
terrae,</hi> muſt be here ſo interpreted, as in 42 <hi>Eliz.</hi> the Bill
is worth the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, it reciteth that divers perſons without any writ
or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment were caſt into priſon, &amp;c. that it might be enacted
that it ſhould not be ſo done hereafter; the anſwer there is, that this 
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116495:15"/> is an Article of the great Charter, this ſhould be
granted, ſo that it ſeems the ſtatute is not taken to be an explanation
of that of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> but the very words of the ſtatute of
<hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will conclude with a little obſervation upon theſe words,
<hi>nec ſuper eum mittimus,</hi> which words of themſelves ſignifie not
ſo much, a man cannot finde any fit ſenſe for them.</p>
                  <p>But my Lord, in the ſeventh year of King <hi>Iohn,</hi> there
was a great Charter by which this ſtatute in the ninth of <hi>Henry</hi> the
third, whereby we are now regulated, was framed, and there the words are,
<hi>nec eum in Carcerem mittimus,</hi> we will not commit him to priſon; that
is, the King himſelf will not: and to juſtifie this, there is a ſtory of
that time in <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> and in that Book this Charter of King
<hi>Iohn</hi> is ſet down at large, which Book is very authentique, and there
it is entred, and in the ninth of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, he ſaith, that
the ſtatute was renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame words with the Charter of King
<hi>Iohn;</hi> and my Lord, he might know it better then others, for he was the
Kings Chronologer in thoſe times: and therefore my Lord, ſince there be
ſo many reaſons, and ſo many preſidents, and ſo many ſtatutes,
which declare that no Free-man whatſoever ought to be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, but
according to the laws of the land; and that the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſubject is
the higheſt inheritance that hee hath; my humble requeſt is, that according
to the ancient laws and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of this Realm, this Gentleman my Client
may be be bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>The Argument of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calthrop</hi> at the Kings Bench Bar,
22 <hi>Novembris, Mich.</hi> 3. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roli Regis.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> being brought to the Kings Bench Bar
with Sir <hi>Edmond Hampden,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Earl,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn
Henning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> who wer alſo brought thither by ſeverall writs of
<hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> with the ſame return, I being aſſigned by the
Court of Kings Bench, upon a petition delivered to be of Councell with 
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116495:16"/> Sir <hi>Iohn Corbet,</hi> did move that Sir <hi>Iohn
Corbet</hi> might bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of his impriſonment, and put in bail, for
I did conceive that the return of this <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> was
inſufficient, both in the matter of the return, and in the manner of the
return, and ſo there ought not to be a longer detaining of Sir <hi>Iohn
Corbet</hi> in priſon: for as unto the manner of the return it is not laid
downe preciſely that Sir <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> is detained in priſon by the
ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all commandment of the King, ſignified by the warrant of the Lords of
the Councell, the which is not a direct affirmation that he is detained by the
ſpeciall command of the King, but that the Lords of the Councell by their
warrant have ſignified unto him that he was committed and ſtill detained by
the ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the King.</p>
                  <p>And howſoever the Lords of the Councell had ſignified that
he was detained by the commandment of the King, yet it may be he was not
detained by the commandment of the King, for their ſignification of the
ſame by warrant may be untrue, and the warrant of the Lords of the Councell
that is returned <hi>in haec ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> importeth that the keeper of the
Gatehouſe rather tooke upon him to return, that was ſignified unto him by
the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Lords of the Councel, that Sir <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> was
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and detained by the ſpeciall commandment of the King, becauſe if
the keeper had taken upon him to affirm it upon his return, then needed he not
to have returned the warrants of the Lords of the Councell, and the warrant it
ſelf ſheweth that hee had onely his information from the Lords of the
Councell; for their warrant is to let the keeper know, that both the firſt
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment, and this direction for the continuing of him in priſon, were and
are by his Majeſties ſpeciall commandment, and I doe not ſee as this
return is made, that an accord upon the caſe can lie upon the keeper of the
Gatehouſe, if Sir <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> was not committed nor detained by the
ſpeciall commandment of the King, ſo long as the warrant of the Lords of
the Councell bee returned as it was made, becauſe hee doth return the ſame
as the Significavit of the Lords by their warrant, Regiſter 65. the writ of
Excommunication <hi>Capiend'</hi> goeth, <hi>Rex vicecom' Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln' S.
ſignificavit nob' venerabilis Pater Henricus Lincolnienſis 
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116495:16"/> Epiſcopus per Literas ſuas Patentes quod R. ſuus
Parochial' pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter ſuam manifeſtam contumac' authoritate ipſius Epiſc.
ordin' excom' eſt nec ſe vult per cenſuram Eccleſiaſticam
juſticiar' &amp;c. tibi praecipimus quod praedict' R. per corpus ſuum
ſecundum conſuetud' Angliae juſtic' &amp;c.</hi> and yet no man will
ſay that there is an information of the King, that <hi>R.</hi> is
excommunicated, but onely that the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> had ſignified
unto him that <hi>R.</hi> was excommunicated: and in <hi>Fitz. Nat. Br.</hi>
663. and <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> 65. it appears that the form of the writ of
Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>deliberand'</hi> is, <hi>Rex Vicecom' London Salut'. Cum
Thom' lay allutar' London qui nuper ad denuntiat. venerabil' Patris Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiep'
Eborum pro contumaciis ſuis ratione contractus in civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te noſtra Eborum
habit' ut dicebat. tanquam excom' &amp; claves Eccleſiae contemnent' per
corp' ſuum ſecundum confuetud' Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae per te juſtic' praecepimus, donec
&amp;c. eſſet ſatisfact' eid' Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epiſcop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d ſatisfaciendum deo et
ſanctae eccleſiae, ſufficientem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſuit cautionem, per quod eidem
Archiepiſcopus offic. Archdiac. London. mutuae viciſſitudin' obtentu
ſcripſit ut ipſum abſolvat ab excom' ſenten' memorata ſicut idem
Archiepiſcopus per Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras ſuas Patentes nob' ſignificavit, Tibi
praecipimus quod praed. Thom' cum tibi conſtare poterit ipſum ab excom'
praedict' per praedict' Official' abſolvi à Priſon' qua detinetur
ſi ea occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one &amp; non alia detineat' in eadem ſine dilatione
deliberari fac'.</hi> And yet it cannot be ſaid, that although the King
recited in his writ that the Archbiſhop had ſignified unto him that he had
written unto the Officiall of the Archdeacon, that the King ſaid that the
Archbiſhop had written, for he doth not affirme ſo much preciſely, but
onely, referreth himſelf unto the Certificate of the Archbiſhop.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plowden</hi> 122. <hi>Buckley</hi> and <hi>Rivers</hi>
caſe, it is put that if a man will bring an action of debt upon an
obligation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that it appeares by the obligation that the defendant
ſtood bound to the plaintiffe in twenty pounds, the which he hath not paid,
this declaration is not good, inſomuch as it is not alledged by matter in
fact, that he was bound unto him in twenty pound, but the deed is alledged by
recitall onely, 21 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. 43.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plowden Com'</hi> 126. <hi>&amp;</hi> 143. <hi>Browning</hi>
and <hi>Beeſtons</hi> caſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116495:17"/> The Abbot of <hi>Waltham</hi> being
appointed collector of a Diſme granted unto the King in diſcharge of
himſelf, in the Exchequer, pleadeth, <hi>Quo inter recordat' Ter. Paſc.
anno</hi> 15. <hi>domini Regis Edvardi</hi> 1. <hi>inter alia continetur quod
R.</hi> 2. had granted unto the predeceſſors of the ſaid Abbot, that he
nor any of his ſucceſſours ſhould be any collectors of any diſmes to
be granted afterwards, and it was adjudged that this plea was ill.</p>
                  <p>For the ſaying [it was contained among the Records,] it is no
preciſe affirmation that the King had granted to his predeceſſors, that
they ſhould be diſcharged of the collecting any diſmes, but it is onely
an allegation by way of recitall, and not by preciſe affirmation, the plea
may not bee good.</p>
                  <p>2 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3 <hi>Mar. Dier</hi> 117. <hi>&amp;</hi> 118.
the plaintiffes reply in barre of all pleadeth, that <hi>Iohn Abbot</hi> of
<hi>W.</hi> was ſeiſed of his lands in right of his Church, and ſo
ſeiſed by the aſſent of the tenant by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture, 14 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4.
<hi>teſtat' quod praedict' Abbat' &amp; convent' de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerunt &amp;
tradiderunt,</hi> unto the plaintiffe, and ruled, that this form of pleading
was ill, inſomuch as it was not alledged by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe affirmation, <hi>quod
demiſerunt, ſed indentura teſtatur, quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerunt;</hi> which is not
ſufficient, inſomuch as it is onely an allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by way of recitall, that
the Indenture doth witneſſe, and the ſame Indenture may witneſſe ſo
much, and yet not be a demiſe.</p>
                  <p>And if in pleading there muſt be direct affirmation of the
mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alledged, then <hi>à fortiore</hi> in a return, which muſt be
more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe then in pleading, and ſo by all the caſes I have formerly
tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, it appeareth that this return is no expreſſe affirmation of the
keeper of the Gatehouſe, that Sir <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> is detained in
priſon by the ſpeciall commandment of the King, but onely an affirmation of
the Lords of the Councell, who had ſignified unto him that his detainment in
priſon was by ſpeciall command of the King.</p>
                  <p>The return which ought to be certain, and punctuall, and
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative, and not by way of information out of another mans mouth, may not
be good, as appeareth by the ſeverall books of our Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:116495:17"/> 23 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rex vic'</hi> 181.
upon a <hi>Homine replegiando,</hi> againſt the Abbot of <hi>C.</hi> the
Sheriffe returneth that he had ſent to the Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe of the Abbot, that
anſwered him that he was the villain of the Abbot, by which he might not make
deliverance, and a <hi>Sicut alias</hi> was awarded, for this return was
inſufficient, inſomuch that he had returned the anſwer of the Bailiffe of
the Abbot, where he ought to have returned the anſwer of the Abbot himſelf
out of his own mouth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Trin.</hi> 22 <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. <hi>Rot.</hi> 46. <hi>parent.
vill' &amp; Burg Eveſque de Norwich, repl'</hi> 68. <hi>Nat. Br. Caſe</hi>
34. <hi>Fitz. Nat. Br.</hi> 65. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.
<hi>Excom'</hi> 29. the caſe appeareth to be ſuch in a treſpaſſe, the
defendant pleadeth, the plaintiffe is excommunicate, and ſheweth forth the
letter of the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> witneſſing that for divers
contumacies, &amp;c. and becauſe he had certified no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communic' done by
himſelf, but by another, the letter of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication was annulled, for the
Biſhop ought to have certified his own act, and not the act of another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hillarii</hi> 21 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Rot.</hi> 37. it
appeareth by the return of an <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> that <hi>Iohn Parker</hi>
was committed to priſon for ſecurity of the peace, and for ſuſpition of
felony, as <hi>per manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum domini Regis nunciatum, per Robertum Peck de
Cliffords</hi> Inne, and upon his return <hi>Iohn Parker</hi> was bailed, for
the return <hi>Commiſſ. fuit per ſpeciale mandatum domini Regis,
nunciatum per Robertum Peck</hi> was not good, inſomuch that it was not a
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect return that he was committed <hi>per mandatum domini Regis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for the firſt point, I conclude that this return is
inſufficient in form, inſomuch that it doth not make a preciſe and direct
return, that he was committed and detained by the ſpeciall command of the
King, but only as he was ſignified by the warrant of the Lords of the
Councel, which will not ſerve the turn; and upon the book of 9 <hi>Hen.</hi>
6. 44. the return of the cauſe of a mans impriſonment ought to be preciſe
and direct upon the <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> inſomuch as thereby to be able to
judge of the cauſe, whether it be ſufficient or not for there may not any
doubt be taken to the return, be it true or falſe, but the Court is to accept
the ſame as true: and if it be falſe, the party muſt take his remedy by
action upon the caſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116495:18"/> And as concerning the matter of the return,
it will reſt upon theſe parts.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, whether the return be that he is detained in priſon
by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall commandment of our Lord the King, be good or not, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
ſhewing the nature of the commandment, or the cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the
commitment is grounded in the return.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, whether the time of the firſt commitment by
the commandment of the King, not appearing to the Court, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to
detain him in priſon.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, whether the impriſonment of the ſubjects without
cauſe ſhewed, but onely by the commandment of the King, be warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table by
the laws and ſtatutes of this Realm.</p>
                  <p>As unto the firſt part, I finde by the books of our law, that
commandments of the King are of ſeverall natures, by ſome of which the
impriſonment of a mans body is utterly unlawfull: and by others of them,
although the impriſonment may be lawfull, yet the continuance of him without
bail or mainpriſe, will be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unlawfull.</p>
                  <p>There is a verball command of the King which is by word of mouth
of the Kings only, and ſuch commandment by the King by the books of our law
will not be ſufficient either to impriſon a man or to continue him in
priſon, 16. 6. <hi>Monſtrans de faict ſi,</hi> upon an action of
treſpaſſe brought for cutting of trees, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant pleadeth that the
place where he cut them is parcell of the Manor of <hi>D,</hi> whereof the King
is ſeiſed in fee, and the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to cut the trees, and the
opinion of the Court there is, that the plea in bar was ill, becauſe he did
not ſhew any ſpeciall commandment of the King, and there it is agreed by
the whole Court, that if the King commandeth one to arreſt another, and the
party commanded did arreſt the other, an action of treſpaſſe or falſe
impriſonment is maintainable againſt the party that arreſted him,
although it were done in the preſence of the King, 39 <hi>H.</hi> 6. 17.
where one juſtifieth the ſeiſure of the goods of a perſon that is
outlawed by the commandment of the King, ſuch a party being no 
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116495:18"/> Officer may not in an action brought againſt him have
any aid of the King; for ſuch a commandment given to one that is not an
Officer, will not any ways avail him that is to juſtifie himſelf by the
return of that commandment.</p>
                  <p>37. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. 10. If the King give me a thing and I take
the ſame by his commandment by word of mouth, it is not juſtified by law,
nothing may paſſe without matter of Record.</p>
                  <p>10 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. 18. it is agreed that
Juſtices may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand one to arreſt another that is in their view or
preſence, but not one that is out of their view or preſence.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Keble</hi> 10 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. 13. ſaid, that where
one is arreſted by a parroll command in their view or preſence, it is
fitting that a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord may be made of it, inſomuch that without ſuch a
record there can hardly be a juſtification in another Term.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, there is a commandment of the King by his
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which according unto <hi>Calvins</hi> caſe in the ſeventh
Report, it is called by him <hi>breve mandatum non remediabile,</hi> and by
vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of ſuch a commandment the King may neither ſeiſe the goods of his
ſubject, nor impriſon his body, as it is reſolved in 42 <hi>Aſſ.
pl.</hi> 5. where it is agreed by all the Juſtices that a Commiſſion to
take a mans goods, or impriſon his body without indictment or ſuit of the
party, or other due proceſſe, is againſt the Law.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, there is a commandment of the King which is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
upon a ſuggeſtion made to the King or to his Councell; and if a man be
committed to priſon by ſuch a ſuggeſtion by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of the King,
it is unlawfull, and not warranted by the law of the Realm.</p>
                  <p>The 25 of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>de
Proviſoribus,</hi> whereas it is contained in the great Charter of the
<hi>Franchiſes</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that none ſhall be impriſoned or
arreſted of his Free-hold or of his Franchiſes, nor of his free cuſtomes
but by the law of the land.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:116495:19"/> It is awarded, conſented and
eſtabliſhed, that from henceforth none ſhall be taken by petition or
ſuggeſtion made to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord the King, or to his Councell, untill
it be by indictment or preſentment of his good and lawfull neighbours, where
ſuch deeds are done in due manner, or by proceſſe made by writ origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
at the Common law, nor that none ſhall be arreſted of his Franchiſes, nor
of his free-hold, unleſſe he be duly brought in, and anſwer, and
forejudged of the ſame by way of law, and if any thing be done againſt the
ſame, it ſhall be redreſſed and holden for nought.</p>
                  <p>37 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. although it be contained in
the great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that no man be taken or impriſoned, or put out of his
free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, without due proceſſe of the law: nevertheleſſe divers
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons make falſe ſuggeſtions to the King himſelf, as well for
malice as otherwiſe, whereof the King is often grieved, and divers of the
Realm put in great damages contrary to the form of the ſame Statute.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore it is ordained, that all they that make ſuch
ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be ſent with their ſuggeſtions to the Chancelour or
Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and they and every of them finde ſureties to purſue their
ſuggeſtions, and endure the ſame pain that the other ſhould have had;
if in caſe that his ſuggeſtion be found untrue, and that then
proceſſe of the law be made againſt them without being taken or
impriſoned againſt the form of the ſame Charter, and other
ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</p>
                  <p>So that it appears by theſe ſeverall ſtatutes, that ſuch
command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the King as are grounded upon ſuggeſtion, either made to
himſelf or to his Councell, for the impriſonment of a man, are againſt
the law.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, I find that there is a commandment of the King which
is made under his hand, with his ſignet, for in the fourth and the fifth of
<hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary, Dier</hi> 162. where the ſtatute of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Ric.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.
reſtraineth the Warden of the Fleet for letting any man at large that is in
upon judgement at the ſuit of any man, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be by writ or other
commandment of the King; It was doubted, whether the Queen by letter under her
hand and privy ſignet, doth give commandment to the Warden of the Fleet to 
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116495:19"/> ſuffer a man that is there in execution to goe about his
buſineſſe, or the affaires of the Queen: whether this be a warrantable
command or not within the Statute: and the Law hath alwayes been conceived upon
that book, that ſuch a commandment is not warrantable by Law, and if ſuch a
command will not ſerve the turn, to give unto a man his liberty, which the
law favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and had the countenance of an Act of Parliament for the doing
of it, then I conceive it ſhould be a more ſtrong caſe, the King ſhould
not have power by his commandment to impriſon a man without due proceſſe
of the Law, and reſtrain him of his liberty when there had been ſo many
Acts of Parliament made for the liberty of the ſubjects.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, I doe finde that there is the commandment of the King
which is by his writ under the Great Seal, or the ſeal of the Court out of
which it iſſueth, <hi>Regiſt. f.</hi> 69. <hi>&amp;</hi> 70. in the writ
<hi>de cautione admittenda,</hi> I find the words, <hi>mandatum Regis</hi>
expounded to be <hi>breve Regis,</hi> for the writ goeth: <hi>Rex vic' Salutem.
Cum nuper ad requiſitionem S. de Iſle Canonici Lincolne venerabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Patris
H. Lincoln. Epiſcopi ipſo in remotis agente Vicarii general. per Literas
ſuas Patentes nobis ſignificantis Nicho. B. dict. Lincoln. Dioc. propter
manifeſtam contumaciam Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ipſius Epiſcopi Ordinar.
excommunicat. eſſe nec ſi velle &amp;c. vobis praeceperimus quod praefat.
&amp;c. ſatisfactum ex parte ipſius N. qui virtute mandati noſtri
praedict. per vos Capt. &amp; in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. noſtra de Newgate detent.
exiſtit, &amp;c. nos nolentes quod praefat. N. per breve noſtrum praedict.
via praecludatur &amp;c. pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequi
poſſit in forma Iuris maxim. &amp;c. integer eſſe debeat, vobis
praecipimus quod ſcire &amp;c. quod ſit &amp;c. quare praedict. N. à
Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona praedict. deliberari non debeat. Rex juſticiar. ſuis de Banco
ſalut. Cum nos nuper ad ſignificationem S. de Iſle &amp;c. uſque ibi
excommunicat. extitiſſe nec ſe velle &amp;c. eſſet ſatisfactum ex
parte ipſius N. virtute manditi noſtri praed. capt. &amp; in Priſona
noſtra de Newgate tuncdetenti, &amp;c. et nolentes eo praetextu prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fato N.
per breve noſtrum praed. via praecludat. quo minus appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lac. ſuae negotium
&amp;c. proceſſerat. &amp; appellant. ſtatut. &amp;c. per breve noſtrum
praeceperimus praefat. vic. quod ſcire face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. <pb n="36" facs="tcp:116495:20"/>
&amp;c. vobis ſignific. &amp; conſult. &amp; circumſpect. in Placitis per
breve praedict. coram vobis pendentibus procedere valeatis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum legem
&amp; conſuetudinem Regni noſtri.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Stamf.</hi> 72. 5 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8. 1.
<hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. ſaith, that every <hi>Capias</hi> in a
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall action is a commandment of the King, for it is <hi>Praecipimus
tibi quod capias &amp;c.</hi> and yet the defendant as there it is ſaid is
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleviſable by the Common law, 7 <hi>R.</hi> 20. <hi>a. Calvins</hi>
caſe, ſaith that there are two kind of writs, <hi>viz. brevia mandatoria
&amp; remedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, &amp; brevia
mandatoria &amp; non remedialia: brevia mandatoria &amp; remedialia,</hi> are
writs of Right, Formedon &amp;c. debts, treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſhortly all
writs reall and perſonall, whereby the party wronged is to recover
ſomewhat, and to be remedied for that wrong which is done unto him.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, I doe finde by our books of Law, and by the Regiſter,
that this ſpeciall <hi>mandatum domini Regis,</hi> is expounded to be his
writ, and that the Law taketh no notice of any other <hi>ſpeciale
mandatum,</hi> then by this writ; the which being ſo when the return is made,
that he is impriſoned and detained in priſon by the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall commandment
of the King, how can the Court adjudge upon this return, that Sir <hi>Iohn
Corbet</hi> ought to be kept in priſon, and not to be bailed, when the nature
of the ſpeciall command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not ſet forth in the return, whereby it may
appear unto the Court that he is not bailable. In <hi>Bracton, c.</hi> 12. 112.
you ſhall ſee a writ reciting, <hi>Praecipimus tibi quod non implacites nec
impl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citari permittas talem de
libero tenemento ſuo in tali villa ſine ſpeciali praecepto noſtro vel
Capitalis Juſticiar' noſtri.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the reaſon of it there is given, <hi>quia nemo de libero
tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſine brevi ſive libello conventionali niſi gratis voluerit
reſpondebit.</hi> So as the exception of ſpeciall commandment by the very
book, appeareth to be <hi>breve ſive libellus conventionalis, Regiſt.</hi>
271. the writ of Manucaption goeth in this manner: <hi>Rex vic. Salut. Cum
nuper aſſignaverimus dilectos et fideles ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros A. B &amp; C. D. ad
inquiſitiones de forſtallariis et tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionibus contra formam
ſtatuti dudum apud Winton. editi in com. tuo faciend. et ad illos quos inde
culpabiles invenirent. capiend. &amp; <pb n="37" facs="tcp:116495:20"/> in Priſona
noſtra ſalvo cuſtod. faciend. donec aliud inde praecepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſemus quod
C. D. et E. pro hujuſmodi forſtallamentis &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſionibus
unde coram praefat. A. B. &amp; C. indict. fuerint, capt. &amp; in Priſona de
L. detent. exiſt. à qua deliberari non poſſunt, ſine mandato
noſtro ſpeciali, Nos volentes eiſdem C. D. &amp; E. gratiaem in hac parte
facere ſpecialem, tibi praecipimus quod ſi praedict. C. D. et E.
occaſione praedict. et non alia in Priſona p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. detineantur, et pro tranſgreſſionibus illis
ſecundum legem &amp; conſuetudinem Regni noſtri Angliae replegiabiles
exiſtunt &amp;c. tunc impos C. D. et E. à Priſona praedict. ſi ea
occaſione et non alia detineantur in eadem interim deliberari facias per
manucapt. ſupradict. et habeas ibi tunc coram praefat. Juſticiar. nomina
manucapt. illorum et hoc breve.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the expoſition of this <hi>ſpeciale mandatum domini
Regis,</hi> mentioned in the writ, is expounded to be <hi>breve domini
Regis,</hi> &amp; thereupon is this writ directed unto the Sheriffe for the
delivery of them.</p>
                  <p>And ſo for the firſt branch of the firſt part: I conclude,
that the ſpeciall command of the King without ſhewing the nature of the
commandment of the Kings, is too generall, and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient; for
he ought to have returned the nature of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of the King, whereby
the Court might have adjudged upon it, whether it were ſuch a commandment
that the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment of Sir <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> be lawfull or not, and
whether it were ſuch a commandment of the King, that although the
impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment were lawfull at the firſt, yet he might be bailed by Law.</p>
                  <p>And as for the generall return of <hi>ſpeciale mandatum domini
Regis,</hi> without ſhewing the cauſe of the impriſonment either
ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall or generall, I hold that for that cauſe alſo the return is
inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, in regard of the <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> which is the
commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King onely, made the 15 of <hi>November.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>According to the <hi>Teſte</hi> of the writ commanding the
keeper of the Gatehouſe to have the body of Sir <hi>Iohn Corbet, una cum 
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116495:21"/> cauſa detentionis et ad ſubjiciendum et recipiendum ea
quae cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria noſtra de eo ad tunc ibid. ordinar. conting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>'.</hi> So as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of the writ being to
ſhew the cauſe of his detaining in priſon, the keeper of the Gatehouſe
doth not give a full anſwer unto the writ, unleſſe the cauſe of the
detainment in priſon be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, and the Court doth not know how to give
their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon him, either for his impriſonment, or for his
diſcharge, according to the purport of the writ, when there is not a cauſe
returned, and foraſmuch as upon an excommengement certified, it hath been
adjudged oftentimes that Certificates were inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent where the cauſe of
the commitment hath not been certified, that the Court might adjudge whether
the Eccleſiaſticall Judges who pronounced the excommunication, had power
over the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall cauſe according to the book of 14 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. 14. 8.
<hi>Rep.</hi> 68. <hi>Trollops</hi> caſe, &amp; 20 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.
Excommengement 9.</p>
                  <p>So upon an <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> in this Court, where a man
hath been committed by the Chancelour of <hi>England,</hi> by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of
<hi>England,</hi> Marches of <hi>Wales,</hi> Warden of the Stanneries, High
Commiſſion, Admiralty, Dutchy, Court of Requeſt, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of
Sewers or Bankrupts, it hath ſeverall times been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged that the return
was inſufficient where the particular cauſe of impriſonment hath not been
ſhewn to the intent that it might appear that thoſe that committed him had
juriſdiction over the cauſe, otherwiſe he ought to be diſcharged by the
Law: &amp; I ſpare to recite particular cauſes in every kinde of theſe,
becauſe there are ſo many preſidents of them in ſeverall ages of every
King of this Realm: and it is an infallible maxime of the Law, That as the
Court of the Kings Bench, and Judges ought not to deny an <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas
corpus</hi> unto any priſoner that ſhall demand the ſame by whomſoever
he be committed, ſo ought the cauſe of his impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment to be ſhewn
upon the return, ſo that the Court may adjudge of the cauſe whether the
cauſe of the impriſonment be lawfull or not: and becauſe I will not
trouble the Court with ſo many preſidents, but ſuch as ſhall ſuit
with the cauſe in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I will onely produce and vouch ſuch
preſidents, whereas the party was committed either by the commandment of the 
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116495:21"/> King, or otherwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e by the commandment of the Privy Councell, which <hi>Stampford.
fol.</hi> 72. tearmeth the mouth of the King, ſuch Acts as are done by the
Privy Councell, being as Acts done by the King himſelf.</p>
                  <p>And in all theſe cauſes you ſhall finde that there is a
cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned as well as a <hi>ſpeciale mandatum domini Regis
&amp;c.</hi> or <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum Privati Concilii domini Regis,</hi> whereby the
Court may adjudge of the cauſe, and bail them if they ſhall ſee
cauſe.</p>
                  <p>In the eighth of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, upon return of an
<hi>Habeas corpus</hi> awarded for the body of one <hi>Roger Sherry,</hi> it
appeareth that he was committed by the Mayor of <hi>Windſor</hi> for
ſuſpition of felony, and <hi>ad ſectam ipſius Regis pro quibuſdam
feloniis et tranſgreſſionibus ac per mandatum domini Regis;</hi> 21
<hi>Hen.</hi> the ſeventh, upon the return of an <hi>Habeas corpus</hi>
ſent for the body of <hi>Hugh Pain,</hi> it appeared that he was committed to
priſon, <hi>per mandatum dominorum Privati Concilii domini Regis pro
ſuſpicione feloniae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Primo Henrici Octavi, Rot.</hi> 9. upon the return of an
<hi>Habeas corpus</hi> ſent for the body of one <hi>Thomas Harriſon</hi>
and others, it appears that they were committed to the Earl of
<hi>Shrewsbury</hi> being Marſhall of the houſhold, <hi>Per mandatum domini
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis, et pro ſuſpicione feloniae, et pro homicidio facto ſuper
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3 &amp; 4 <hi>Philip. et Mariae,</hi> upon a return of an
<hi>Habeas corpus</hi> ſent for the body of one <hi>Peter Man,</hi> it
appeareth that he was committed <hi>pro ſuſpicione feloniae, ac per
mandatum domini Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis et Reginae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>4 &amp; 5 <hi>Philippi et Mariae,</hi> upon the return of an
<hi>Habeas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> ſent for the body of one <hi>Thomas Newport,</hi> it
appeared that he was committed to the Tower, <hi>pro ſuſpicione contrafact,
mc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netae per privatum Concilium domini Regis et Reginae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>33 <hi>Elizabeth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> upon the return of an <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> for the body of
one <hi>Lawrence Brown;</hi> it appeareth that he was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Per
mandatum Privati Conſilii dominae Reginae pro diverſis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>auſis ipſam Reginam tangen, ac
etiam pro ſuſpicione proditic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:116495:22"/> So as by all theſe preſidents it
appeareth where the returne is either <hi>Per mandatum domini Regis,</hi> or
<hi>Per mandatum domine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Privati Concilii domini Regis;</hi> there is alſo
a cauſe over and beſides the <hi>mandatum</hi> returned, as unto that which
may be objected, that <hi>per mandatum domini Regis,</hi> or <hi>Privati
Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii domini Regis</hi> is a good return of his impriſonment I
anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that there is a cauſe, for it is not to be preſumed
that the King or Councell would commit one to priſon without ſome offence,
and therefore this <hi>mandatum</hi> being occaſioned by the offence or
fault, the offence or fault muſt be the cauſe, and not the command of the
King or Councell which is occaſioned by the cauſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it appears that the juriſdiction of the Privy
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell is a limited juriſdiction, for they have no power in all cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
their power being reſtrained in certain cauſes by ſeverall Acts of
Parliament, 
<note place="margin">Vide 4 Inſtit. fol. 53.</note> as it
appeareth by the ſtatute of 20 <hi>Edward</hi> the third, <hi>c.</hi> 11. 25
<hi>Ed.</hi> the third <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 4. the private petition
in Parliament permitted in the 1 of <hi>R.</hi> 2. where the Commons pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition
that the Privy Councell might not make any Ordinance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Common Law,
Cuſtomes or Statutes of the Realm; the fourth of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth,
<hi>ca.</hi> 3. 13 <hi>Hen.</hi> the fourth, 7. 31 <hi>H.</hi> the ſixth, and
their juriſdictions being a limited juriſdiction, the cauſe and grounds
of their commitment ought to appear, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may appear if the Lords of the
Councell did commit him for ſuch a cauſe as was within their
juriſdiction: for if they did command me to be committed to priſon for a
cauſe whereof they had not juriſdiction, the Court ought to diſcharge me
of this impriſonment, and howſoever the King is <hi>Vicarius Dei in
terra,</hi> yet <hi>Bracton, cap.</hi> 8. <hi>fol.</hi> 107. ſaith, <hi>quod
nihil aliud poteſt Rex in terris cum ſit Miniſter Dei &amp; Vicarius,
quam ſolum quod de jure poteſt. nec obſtat, quod dicitur quod Principi
placet, legis habet vigorem, quia ſequitur in fine legis cum lege Regia quae
de ejus imperio lata eſt, id eſt non quicquid de voluntate Regis temere
praeſumptum eſt, ſed animo condendi Jura, ſed quod con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio
Magiſtratuum ſuorum Rege author. praeſtant et habita ſuper hoc
deliberatione et tract. rect. fuer. definit. Poteſtat. <pb n="41" facs="tcp:116495:22"/>
itaque ſuajuris eſt, &amp; non injuriae.</hi> The which being ſo, then
alſo it ought to appear upon what cauſe the King committeth one to
priſon, whereby the Judges which are indifferent between the King and his
Subjects, may judge whether his commitment be againſt the Laws and Statutes
of this Realm or not.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it is to be obſerved, that the Kings command by his
Writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> is ſince the commandment of the King for his
commitment, and this being the latter commandement, ought to be obeyed;
wherefore that commanding a return of the body <hi>cum cauſa
detentionis,</hi> there muſt be a return of ſome other cauſe then <hi>Per
mandatum domini Regis,</hi> the ſame commandment being before the return of
the Writ.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paſch.</hi> 9 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>pl.</hi> 30.
<hi>fol.</hi> 56. upon a Writ of <hi>Ceſſavit</hi> brought in the County of
<hi>Northumberland,</hi> the Defendants plead, That by reaſon the Country
being deſtroyed by Wars with the Scots, King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond
gave command that no Writ of <hi>Ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit</hi> ſhould be brought during
the Wars with <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that the King had ſent his Writ to
ſurceaſe the Plea, and he averreth that the Wars with <hi>Scotland</hi> did
continue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hearle</hi> that giveth the Rule ſaith, That we have
command by the King that now is, to hold this Plea, wherefore we will not
ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe for any Writ of the King that is dead; and ſo upon all theſe
reaſons and preſidents formerly alledged, I conclude, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn that
Sir <hi>John Corbet</hi> was committed and detained in priſon, <hi>Per
ſpeciale mandatum domini Regis,</hi> without ſhewing the nature of the
commandement by which the Court may judge whether the commandement be of ſuch
a nature as he ought to be detained in priſon, and that without ſhewing the
cauſe upon which the commandement of the King is grounded, is not good. As
unto the ſecond part, which is, Whether the time of the commitment by the
return of the Writ, not appearing unto the Court, the Court ought to detain him
in priſon or no?</p>
                  <p>I conceive that he ought not to be continued in priſon
admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <pb n="42" facs="tcp:116495:23"/> that the firſt commitment by the command of
the King were lawfull, yet when he hath continued in priſon by ſuch
reaſonable time as may be thought fit for that offence for which he is
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, he ought to be brought to anſwer, and not to continue ſtill in
priſon without being brought to anſwer.</p>
                  <p>For it appears by the Books of our Laws, that liberty is a thing
ſo favoured by the Law, that the Law will not ſuffer the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a
man in priſon for any longer time then of neceſſity it muſt; and
therefore the Law will neither ſuffer the party, Sheriffs or Judges to
continue a man in priſon by their power and their pleaſure, but doth
ſpeed the delivery of a man out of priſon, with as reaſonable expedition
as may be.</p>
                  <p>And upon this reaſon it is reſolved in 1 <hi>&amp;</hi> 2
<hi>El. Dyer</hi> 175. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. 13. That howſoever
the Law alloweth that there may be no terme between the teſt of an originall
Writ and the return of the ſame, where there is only a ſummons, and no
impriſonment of the body, yet it will not allow that there ſhall be a term
between the teſt of a Writ of <hi>Capias,</hi> and the return of the ſame,
where the body of a man is to be impriſoned, inſomuch that it will give no
way that the party ſhall have no power to continue the body of a man
impriſoned any longer time then needs muſt. 39 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 7. 10
<hi>H.</hi> 7. 11. 6 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 69. 11. <hi>E.</hi> 4. 9. 48 <hi>E.</hi> 3.
1. 17 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 1 <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kellawaies</hi> Reports do all agree, that if a
<hi>Capias</hi> ſhall be awar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt a man for the apprehending of his
body, and the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe will return the <hi>Capias,</hi> that is awarded
againſt the party, a <hi>non eſt inventus,</hi> or that <hi>languidus eſt
in priſona,</hi> yet the Law will allow the party againſt whom it is
awarded for the avoiding of his corporall penance and dures of impriſonment,
to appear <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> and for to anſwer.</p>
                  <p>For the Law will not allow the Sheriffe by his falſe return to
keep one in priſon longer then needs muſt, 38 <hi>Aſſ. pl.</hi> 22.
<hi>Brooks</hi> impriſonment 100. ſaith, That it was determined in
Parliament that a man is not to be detained in priſon after he hath made
ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his fine for his impriſonment, therefore I deſire your
Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <pb n="43" facs="tcp:116495:23"/> that Sir <hi>John Corbet</hi> may not be kept
longer in durance, but be diſcharged according to the Law.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>The Lord Chief Juſtice his Speech.</head>
               <sp>
                  <p>Maſter Atturney, you have heard many learned Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, if
you be provided to anſwer preſently, we will hear you, but if you will have
a longer day for that you are not provided to argue, you may, we will give it
you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doderidge.</speaker>
                  <p>If you will you may ſee theſe preſidents, it may be you
have not ſeen ſome of them, and we muſt ſee them too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Heath</hi> Atturney.</speaker>
                  <p>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip, the Gentlemen that be of
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell with the Knights at the Barre, they have ſaid much, and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
very long for their Clients, and to good purpoſe and perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently. It is a
cauſe that carrieth with it a great deal of weight, both towards the King and
his Subjects alſo, and I am not ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to put my ſelf upon the main
point of this cauſe, when it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt time for your Lordſhip to
riſe.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, the Gentlemen have ſeverally ſpoken, and given and
inſiſted upon ſeverall reaſons, and they have cited many preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.
I could ſay ſomething of them at this preſent, and that ſome of them
have been miſtaken; and therefore I beſeech your Lordſhip that I may have
time to anſwer, that I may not wrong the cauſe of the Kings part, or
ſlight the cauſe on the Subjects part.</p>
                  <p>But that which I deſire to ſay now, is, that theſe
Gentlemen have all of them gone in one form to divide the cauſe into two
parts: 
<list>
                        <item>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">part </seg>1</label> The firſt, the form of the
Return.</item>
                        <item> 
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">part </seg>2</label> The ſecond, the matter of
the Return.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:116495:24"/> For the form, me thinks we may put an end
to that now, if your Lordſhip pleaſe, that we may have no return to that
ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day, but I may apply my ſelf unto the matter of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
                  <p>To the form of the Return they have taken divers exceptions, but
they eſpecially inſiſted upon two main heads:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that the Return is not good, becauſe it is not an
abſolute Return: I confeſſe the ground is well laid, and the Major is
good, that if this Return be not poſitively the Return of the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the
<hi>Fleet</hi> himſelf, but the relation of another, it is no good Return,
therefore I need ſpend no time in that, the ground being well laid; but under
your Lordſhips favour, the Major propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I deny, we differ onely in
that, for I ſay that this Return is certain, and that it is not the words of
any man elſe, but the expreſs words of the Warden himſelf, and that this
is added <hi>ex abundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti</hi> to give ſatisfaction to the Court, that he
had order to make the Return; therefore I deſire your Lordſhip to caſt
your eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſubſtance of the Return, and diſtinguiſh it into
parts.</p>
                  <p>The words are, <hi>Detentus eſt in priſona ſub cuſtodia
mea per ſpeciale Mandatum domini Regis mihi ſignificatum per Warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
duorum Privati concilii dicti domini Regis, &amp;c.</hi> If he had turned
theſe words, and ſaid, <hi>Detent' eſt prout mihi ſignificat' per
Warrantum duorum Privati concilii per ſpeciale mandatum domini Regis,</hi>
then it might be taken to be the words of the Lords of the Councell, but the
firſt words being poſitive, <hi>Detentus eſt per ſpeciale mandatum
domini Regis,</hi> that is ſufficient, and the reſt is ſurpluſage, and
he doth not ſay, <hi>prout mihi ſignificut,</hi> but <hi>mihi
ſignificat</hi> onely, which is abſolute, and the reſolution thereof
reſteth more in your Lordſhips expounding of the words, then in putting any
caſe upon them.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond exception is taken to the form of the Return, for
that there is not the cauſe of the impriſonment returned, but of the
detaining alone.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, I ſay no more to that but this, No man is bound 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116495:24"/> to anſwer more then that which is the contents of the
Writ, I know the Writ, it may be to know ſpecially the cauſe of the
detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or what the cauſe of the caption is onely, and if the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer
make anſwer to that which is required of him in the Writ, it is ſufficient,
it may be there be preſidents both ways, I am ſure there are detentions
onely, and there is no cauſe why the Officer ſhould ſhew the time of his
commitment, but if the Priſoner ſhall deſire it, your Lordſhip may
grant him a Writ to ſhew the cauſe both of his caption and detention
alſo.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, they ſay that this Return is uncertain, and that it
is the Warrant of the Lords of the Councell, and not of the King, by which he
is committed.</p>
                  <p>For that my Lord I ſay, that if it had all been left out, and
he had onely ſaid, <hi>Detentus fuit per ſpeciale mandatum domini
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis,</hi> it had been ſufficient, but when he doth more it is
ſuperfluous and not neceſſary, for it appeared before by whom he was
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and when he returns the Warrant of the Lords of the Councell, it is
not their words that commit him, but they being the Repreſentative Body of
the King, they doe expreſſe what the Kings command is, but they ſignifie
nothing of their own, and therefore I deſire your Lordſhip to deliver your
opinion in that point of the Return, whether it be poſitive or no.</p>
                  <p>This cauſe as it greatly concerns the Subjects, ſo it much
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the King too, I am ſorry there ſhould be any occaſion to bring
theſe things in queſtion, but ſince it is now here, I hope I ſhall give
ſatisfaction to your Lordſhip, and to the parties too, and I deſire that
I may have Munday for it.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Hide</hi> Chief Juſtice.</head>
               <sp>
                  <p>I think it is not beſt for us to declare our opinions by
peece-meals, but upon all the caſe together, and as well as you are a
ſtranger to the Return, ſo are we, and <pb n="46" facs="tcp:116495:25"/> there be many
preſidents and Acts of Parliament not printed, which we muſt ſee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doderidge.</speaker>
                  <p>This is the greateſt cauſe that ever I know in this Court,
our Judgements that we give between party and party, between the King and the
meaneſt Subject, ought to be maturely adviſed on, for ſo are the entries
of our judgements, <hi>Quod matura delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione habita.</hi> It was judged,
&amp;c. And we muſt ſee the preſidents and Acts of Parliament, that we
hear mentioned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſtice <hi>Jones.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Maſter Atturney, if it be ſo that the Law of <hi>Magna
Charta</hi> and other Statutes be now in force, and the gentlemen be not
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by this Court, how ſhall they be delivered? apply your ſelf to
ſhew us any other way to deliver them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doderidge.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, or elſe they ſhall have a perpetuall
impriſonment.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Per Curiam.</head>
               <p>Munday was appointed for the Atturneys Argument, and in the
interim the Councell for the gentlemen were by order appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for to attend
the Judges with all the preſidents and unprinted Statutes which they
mentioned, and that they ſhould let the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney ſee them alſo.</p>
               <p>And the gentlemen being asked if they deſired to come again,
anſwered they did, and a Rule was entred for it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:116495:25"/>
            <head>
               <hi>On Munday the</hi> 27 <hi>of Tertio Michaelis</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               <hi>Caroli Regis in Banco Regis.</hi> Sir <hi>John Corbet,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter
Earle,</hi> Sir <hi>Edmund Hampden,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Henningham</hi>
Knights, were brought to the Barre.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Heath</hi> Atturney Generall.</speaker>
               <p>MAY it pleaſe your Lordſhip, theſe gentlemen, Sir <hi>Walter
Earle,</hi> Sir <hi>John Corbet,</hi> Sir <hi>Edmund Hampden,</hi> and Sir
<hi>John Henningham,</hi> upon their motion to this Court to have their
<hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> and that themſelves and the cauſe of their
detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them in their ſeverall Priſons might be brought before your
Lordſhip, had it granted to them.</p>
               <p>My Lord, at the firſt motion of it, the knowledge thereof of
comming, and that they had ſuch a deſire, his Majeſty was very willing to
grant unto them (as to all his Subjects) this common caſe of Juſtice, and
though it be a caſe which concerns himſelf in a high degree, yet he hath
been ſo gracious and ſo juſt as not to refuſe to leave the examination
and determination thereof to the Laws of this Kingdome.</p>
               <p>My Lord, it is very true that this is a very great Cauſe, and
hath raiſed a great expectation, and for the manner of it more then was
neceſſary; but my Lord, I am afraid theſe gentlemen whom it concerns,
have rather adviſed their Councell, then their Councell them: but I ſhall
take the caſe as now I finde it, and as the gentlemens Councell on the other
ſide have led me the way to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:116495:26"/> My Lord, the exceptions that have been taken
by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell on the other ſide, to the Return made by the Warden of the
<hi>Fleet,</hi> and the reſt of the Guardians of ſeverall Priſons, have
been two, for renewing of your Lordſhips memory we will read one of the
Returns, they are all alike.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>Then the Return was read for Sir <hi>John Henningham</hi> by
Maſter <hi>Keeling.</hi>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Heath</hi> Atturney.</speaker>
               <p>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip, againſt this Return the
Councell of the Gentlemen have taken ſome exceptions, and have divided their
objections into two main points, The one the form the other the matter; To the
form they have objected four ſeverall things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the Return is not poſitive, but referred to the
ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation made by another, as the Lords of the Councell.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the Keepers of the Priſons have not returned the
cauſe of the commitment, but the cauſe of the cauſe, which is not
good.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that the Return is imperfect, for that it ſhews onely
the cauſe of the detaining in Priſon, and not the cauſe of the firſt
commitment.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, that the Return is contradictory in it ſelf, for
that in the firſt part thereof there is a certification that the detaining of
theſe gentlemen in priſon, is <hi>Per ſpeciale mandatum domini
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis;</hi> and when the Warrant of the Lords of the Councell is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it
appears that the commitment is by the command of the King, ſignified by the
Lords of the Councell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips favour, I will give a
ſeverall anſwer to every of theſe ſeverall objections: And for the
firſt, that the Return, is not poſitive and affirmative, but depends upon
and hath relation to ſome other, and therefore it is not good; I doe agree
that the ground is true, that if the Return be not poſitive it is not good,
we differ onely in the Minor, That the Return is not poſitive and
affirmative, for I agree that theſe Book caſes that have been put are good
Law, as 27 <hi>Aſſ. pl.</hi> 65. that if the Sheriffe return that he hath
ſent to the <pb n="49" facs="tcp:116495:26"/> Bailiffe of the hundred, and he gives him
that anſwer, that is no good Return; for the Sheriffs ought to make the
Return as of his own act without naming of the Bailiffe of the Hundred in his
Return; for if he return, <hi>Quod mandavi Ballivo itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranti qui habet
Retorn. omnium Brevium &amp; executionem eorund, per Cartam domini Regis qui
mihi dedit nullum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſum;</hi> this is not good if he were not Bailiffe
of a Franchiſe or Signiory, for ſo is 21 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>fol.</hi>
4.</p>
               <p>There hath been cited to maintain theſe objections, 20
<hi>Ed.</hi> 3. the Record I have peruſed, and there I finde that the
Biſhop ſaid, that it is found in <hi>Archivis</hi> in the Record &amp;c.
that he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, but it was found to be in <hi>Archivis</hi>
&amp;c. and that is no poſitive return: that it is ſo I will oppugne what
hath been ſaid by the Councell on the other ſide, it muſt be granted that
if the return here be not poſitive, it is imperfect, and in 5 <hi>H.</hi> 7.
28. it is ſaid that an imperfect return is no return at all, it is all one;
but if the return was ſo, that was not much ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, for then it were but
temporary, and it might be amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but my Lord they have miſtaken the minor
propoſition, for they have it as granted that there is an imperfect returne
from the Lords of the Councell; my Lord I ſhall intreat you to caſt your
eyes upon the Return, and you ſhall finde the firſt words poſitive and
affirmative: the words are, <hi>Quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentus eſt ſub cuſtodia mea per
ſpeciale mandatum domini Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis:</hi> the other words <hi>mihi
ſignificatum,</hi> they follow after but are not part of the affirmation made
before it; but if they will have it as they ſeem to underſtand it, then
they muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the words thus: <hi>Quod teſtificatum,</hi> or
<hi>ſignificatum eſt mihi per dominos Privati Concilii quod detentus eſt
per ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciale mandatum domini Regis,</hi> and then indeed it had not been
their own proper return, but the ſignification of another, The Lords of the
Councell, the turning of the ſentence will reſolve this point, the thing it
ſelf muſt ſpeak for it ſelfe, I conceive by your Lordſhips favour,
that it is plain and cleare here is a poſitive Return, that the detaining is
by the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King: and the reſt of the Return is rather
ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <pb n="50" facs="tcp:116495:27"/> to my ſelf and the Court, then
otherwiſe any part of the Return.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Objection hath dependence upon this, as that he hath
returned the cauſe of the cauſe, and not the cauſe of it ſelf, wherein
under your Lordſhips favour they are utterly miſtaken; for the Return is
affirmative, <hi>Ego Iohannes Liloe teſtifico; &amp;c.</hi> I know that among
the Logicians there are two cauſes, there is <hi>Cauſa cauſans,</hi> and
<hi>Cauſa causſata,</hi> the <hi>cauſa cauſans</hi> here in this caſe
is not the warrant from the Lords of the Councell, for that is <hi>cauſa
cauſata:</hi> but the Primary and Originall cauſe, which is <hi>cauſa
cauſans,</hi> is <hi>ſpeciale mandatum domini Regis;</hi> the other is but
the Councels ſignification or teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or warrant for him that made
the Return.</p>
               <p>To the third Objection, that the Return is imperfect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
it ſhews only the cauſe of the detaining in priſon, and not the cauſe
of the firſt commitment.</p>
               <p>My Lords, for that I ſhall not inſiſt much upon it, for that
I did ſay the laſt day which I muſt ſay again, it is ſufficient for
an Officer of the Law to anſwer that point of the Writ which is in
command.</p>
               <p>Will your Lordſhip pleaſe to hear the Writ read, and then to
ſee whether the Wardens of the priſons have not made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſo much
as was in command?</p>
            </sp>
            <p>Then the Writ was read by Maſter <hi>Keeling.</hi>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Heath</hi> Atturney Generall.</speaker>
               <p>My Lord, the Writ it ſelfe clears the Objection, for it is to
have the party mentioned in it, and the cauſe of his detention returned into
this Court, and therefore the anſwer to that is ſufficient. Onely my Lord,
the Warden of the Fleet, and the reſt of the keepers of the priſons, had
dealt prudently in their proceedings, if they had onely ſaid that they were
detained <hi>Per ſpeciale Mandatum Domini Regis,</hi> and it had been good,
and <pb n="51" facs="tcp:116495:27"/> they might have omitted the reſt: but becauſe if
they ſhould make a falſe Return they were liable to the actions of the
party, they did diſcreetly to have the certification of the Lords of the
Councell in ſuſpition, that if this Return was not true they were liable to
the actions of theſe Gentlemen.</p>
               <p>In 9 <hi>H.</hi> 6. 40. 44. it is ſaid, that whatſoever the
cauſe be that is returned, it muſt be accepted by the Court, they muſt
not doubt of the truth of the Return, and the Officer that ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn it
is liable to an action if the Return be falſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Guardian of
the priſons did wiſely becauſe they knew this was a caſe of great
expectation to ſhew from whom they had their warrant, and ſo to ſee
whether the cauſe returned bee true or not.</p>
               <p>The laſt Objection to the Return is, that it is contradictory in
it ſelf, as that the firſt part of it is, that they are detained in
priſon, <hi>Per ſpeciale mandatum Domini Regis,</hi> but in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of it, it ſhews that they are detained by the command of the Lords of the
Councell, for the words of their warrant are to require you ſtill to detain
him, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But my Lord, if they will be pleaſed to ſee the whole war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
together, they ſhall finde that the Lords of the Councell ſpeak not their
own words or command in that warrant, but they ſay that you are to take
notice of it as the words and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the King; for my Lord, the Lords of
the Councell are the ſervants to the King, they ſignifie his Majeſties
pleaſure to your Lordſhip, and they ſay it is his Majeſties pleaſure
you ſhould know that the firſt commitment &amp; this preſent detaining
him in priſon, are by his Majeſties ſpeciall commandment.</p>
               <p>And this my Lord is all that I will ſay for the ſufficiency of
the form of the Return, to prove that it is ſufficient.</p>
               <p>Touching the matter of the Return the main point thereof, it is
but a ſingle queſtion, and I hope my Lord of no great difficulty, and that
is whether they be repleviſable or not repleviſable. It <pb n="52" facs="tcp:116495:28"/> appears that the commitment is not in a legall and ordinary way, but
that it is <hi>per ſpeciale mandatum domini Regis,</hi> which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies not
onely the fact done, but ſo extraordinarily done, that it is notorious to be
his Majeſties immediate Act and will, it ſhould be ſo; whether in this
caſe they ſhould be bailable or not in this Court, which I acknowledge to
be the higheſt Court of Judicature for ſuch a caſe as is in
queſtion.</p>
               <p>The Councell on the other ſide deſire that they may be
bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and have concluded that they may not be remaunded, their grounds of
argument (though they were many that did ſpeak) I have in my collection
divided into five points:</p>
               <p>The firſt was reaſons that they muſt be ſo, ariſing from
the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences that would fall to the ſubjects, if it ſhould not be
ſo in the main points of their liberty.</p>
               <p>The ſecond was, they ſhewed divers Authorities out of their
Law books, which they endeavoured to apply.</p>
               <p>The third was, Petition of the Commons anſwered by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
Kings in Parliament.</p>
               <p>The fourth was, Acts of Parliament in Print.</p>
               <p>The laſt was, Preſidents of divers times, which they alledged
to prove, that men committed by the Kings commandment, and by the commandment
of the Lords of the Privy Councell, which I conceive to be all one, for the
body of the Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell repreſents the King himſelf, that upon ſuch
commitment in ſuch cauſes men have been bailed.</p>
               <p>In the courſe of my Arguments, I will follow their method:
firſt, to anſwer their reaſons, and then thoſe Books which they have
cited, which I conceive to be pertinent to this queſtion, and then the
Petition and Anſwer made in Parliament, and then their Acts of Parliament,
next their Preſidents; and laſtly, I <pb n="53" facs="tcp:116495:28"/> will give your
Lordſhip ſome reaſons of my owne, which I hope ſhall ſufficiently
ſatisfie your Lordſhip and all others but the parties themſelves, for I
except them.</p>
               <p>My Lord, the great and mighty reaſon that they inſiſted
upon, was the inconveniences that might come to the ſubjects in their
liberties, if this Return ſhould be good, and this reaſon they inferred out
of Records and Books of the Common Law, which gives the liberty of the
ſubjects; I doe acknowledge that the liberty of the ſubject is juſt, and
that it is the inheritance of the ſubject, but yet it is their inheritance
<hi>ſecundum legem terrae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lords, they put many caſes likewiſe to enforce it, 1
<hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Eliz. Dier fo.</hi> 175. that the continuance of a
<hi>Capias</hi> ſhall bee from Term to Term, without Term betwixt, becauſe
other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the party defendant may be kept too long in priſon, and 38
<hi>Aſſ. pl.</hi> 22. <hi>Broke tit.</hi> Impriſonment 100. that
impriſonment is but to detaine the party till he have made fine to the King,
and therefore the King cannot juſtly detain him in priſon after the fine
tendred, and 16 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>monſtrans de faictz</hi> 182. if the King
command me to arreſt a man, and thereupon I doe arreſt him, he may have an
action of falſe impriſonment, or of treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, though
it be done in the Kings preſence, and 1 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 4. the diſcourſe
of <hi>Huſſey,</hi> where he ſaith that Sir <hi>John Markham</hi>
delivered unto King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, that hee ſhould not arreſt
upon treaſon or felony any of his ſubjects, becauſe hee could not wrong
his ſubjects by ſuch arreſt, for they could not have remedy againſt
him.<note place="margin">Prerogative, Br. 139.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe my Lord are the cauſes that they inſiſted upon for
this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>To the two firſt, I ſhall give but one anſwer, which is that
the reſtraint in theſe two caſes, and moſt of the other caſes before
cited, appears to be in the ordinary courſe of Judicature fit for
<hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall, and not for the Kings Councell Table. A writ of
<hi>Capias</hi> was the firſt originall of it, and therefore not to be
applied to the cauſe of ours.</p>
               <p>And for the other two caſes, the law preſumeth that the
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <pb n="54" facs="tcp:116495:29"/> part of them is not ſo proper for the Majeſty
of a King, who ever doth theſe things by his ſubordinate Officers; But that
the ſubject ſhould not be committed by the King, was never heard of, for
the King may commit any man at his pleaſure, but that is not our caſe: but
whether when the King hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted one, he muſt render a cauſe of that
commitment, that it may appear whether the party be bailable or not, or elſe
the party muſt be delivered.</p>
               <p>The Book 9 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 16. <hi>pl.</hi> 30. cited
of a Ceſſavit, the King having by Proclamation commanded that in the County
of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> no Ceſſavit ſhould be brought, &amp;c.
du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the war; the tenant pleadeth this command, and it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed him, and
he that notwithſtanding was commanded to plead, but the reaſon thereof was,
becauſe the commandment thereof was given by <hi>E.</hi> 2. who being dead,
the commandment was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined.</p>
               <p>The Book of <hi>Edward</hi> the third 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 16. is
indeed where the commandment was given by the ſame King, and that was
likewiſe denyed him, for the King cannot command your Lordſhip to any other
Court of Juſtice, to proceed otherwiſe then according to the Laws of this
kingdome, for it is part of your Lordſhips oath to judge according to the Law
of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But my Lord, there is a great difference between thoſe
legall commands, and that abſolute <hi>Poteſtas,</hi> that a Soveraign
hath, by which a King commands; but when I call it <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luta
poteſtas,</hi> I doe not mean that it is ſuch a power as that a King may
doe what he pleaſeth, for he hath rules to governe himſelf by, as well as
your Lordſhip, who are ſubordinate Judges under him, the difference is, the
King is the head of the ſame fountaine of Juſtice, which your Lordſhip
adminiſters to all his ſubjects, all Juſtice is derived from him, and
what he doth, he doth not as a private perſon, but as the Head of the
Common-wealth, as <hi>Iuſticiarius Regni,</hi> yea the very eſſence of
Juſtice under God upon earth, is in him: and ſhall not wee generally, not
as ſubjects onely, but as Lawyers, who governe themſelves by the rules of
the Law, ſubmit to his command, but make inquiries whether they be lawfull,
and ſay that the King <pb n="55" facs="tcp:116495:29"/> doth not this or that in courſe
of Juſtice?</p>
               <p>If your Lordſhip ſitting here ſhall proceed according to
Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, who calleth your actions in queſtion, except in your own
Judgements, you ſee ſome errour in the proceeding, and then you are
ſubject to a writ of Errour.</p>
               <p>But who ſhall call in queſtion the Actions or the Juſtice of
the King, who is not to give any account for them? as in this our caſe, that
he commits a ſubject and ſhews no cauſe for it.</p>
               <p>The King commits and often ſhews no cauſe, for it is
ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times generally, <hi>Per ſpecial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mandatum domini Regis,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Pro certis cauſis
ipſum dominum Regem moventibus;</hi> but if the King doe this, ſhall it not
bee good? it is all one when the commitment is <hi>Per ſpeciale mandatum
domini Regis,</hi> and when it is <hi>Pro certis cauſis ipſum dominum Regem
moventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> and it is the ſame if the commitment be <hi>Certis de
cauſis ipſum dominum Regem tangentibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And my Lord, unleſſe the Return to you doth open the
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of the commitment, your Lordſhip cannot judge whether the party
ought by Law to be remaunded, or delivered: and therefore if the King allow and
give warrant to thoſe that make the Return, that they ſhall expreſſe
the cauſe of the commitment, as many times he doth, either for ſuſpition
of felony, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king money, or the like; we ſhall ſhew your Lordſhip
that in theſe cauſes this Court in his Juriſdiction were proper to try
theſe criminall cauſes, and your Lordſhip doth proceed in them although
the commitment be <hi>Per ſpeciale mandatum domini Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis,</hi> which hath
not ſecret in it in theſe cauſes, for with the warrant he ſendeth your
Lordſhip the cauſe of the committing, and when theſe warrants are made
and brought into this Court, your Lordſhip may proceed, but if there be no
cauſe expreſſed, this Court hath always uſed to remaund them for it
hath been uſed, and it is to be intended a matter of State, and that it is
not ripe nor timely for it to appear.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:116495:30"/> My Lord, the main fundamentall grounds of
Arguments upon this caſe beginnes with <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> from thence
have grown ſtates for explanation thereof, ſeverall Petitions of
Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Preſidents for expedition, I ſhall give anſwers to them
all.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> in the 29 Chapter, hath theſe words,
No Free-man ſhall be taken nor impriſoned or diſſeiſed of his
free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, liberties, nor free cuſtomes, nor be outlawed, or exiled, nor any
other way deſtroyed, nor we will not paſſe upon him nor condemn him, but
by lawfull Judgement of his Peers, or by the Law of the Realm.</p>
               <p>My Lord, this ſtatute hath been many times confirmed, the Lord
<hi>Coke</hi> numbred up the number to be about twenty, and we are to conclude
on this, it is the foundation of our liberties.</p>
               <p>No Free-man can be impriſoned but by <hi>legale judicium Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium
ſuorum, aut per legem terrae.</hi> But will they have it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that
no man ſhould be committed, but firſt he ſhall be indicted or
preſented? I think that no learned man will offer that, for certainly there
is no Juſtice of Peace in a County, nor Conſtable within a Town, but he
doth otherwiſe, and might commit before an Indictment can be drawn or a
Preſentment can be made: what then is meant by theſe words, <hi>Per legem
ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae?</hi> if any man ſhall ſay this doth not warrant that the King may
for reaſons moving him commit a man, and not be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for it, neither
to the party, nor (under your Lordſhips fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour) unto any Court of Juſtice,
but to the High Court of Heaven; I doe deny it, and will prove it by your
ſtatutes.</p>
               <p>My Lord, it was urged by the Councell on the other ſide, that
our printed <hi>Magna Charta</hi> which ſaith, <hi>nec ſuper eum
mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> are miſtaken, and that in divers Manuſcripts it is
expreſly ſet down to be <hi>nec eum in Carcerem mittimus.</hi> I cannot
judge of the Manuſcripts that I have not ſeen, but my Lord I have one here
by me, which was written many Ages agoe, and the words in print are word for
word as that that is here written.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:116495:30"/> Then they ſay that <hi>Matthew Paris</hi>
ſets it downe ſo in his ſtory; my Lord, we doe not govern our ſelves by
Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, but to anſwer that of <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> he reports a thing
done in King <hi>Iohns</hi> time, but it was then but thought on, and it was
enacted in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and there bee many things
ſaid to be done in <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> which were not, and many things
omitted by him which were done.</p>
               <p>This Charter was but in election in the time of King
<hi>John,</hi> and then it might be, <hi>nec eum in Carcerem mittimus,</hi> but
it was not enacted till the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and then that was
omitted, and the Charter granted as now we have it.</p>
               <p>But if they doe ſee no more then I in this clauſe, I know not
why we ſhould contend about theſe words, ſeeing the firſt part of this
ſtatute ſaith, <hi>Nemo impriſonetur,</hi> why then may not I ſay as
well, <hi>nec eum in carcerem mittimus?</hi> I ſee no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the
words, and therefore my Lord, I ſhall not inſiſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer upon the
literall expoſition of the words of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> but I will
reſort to the reſt of it which is expreſt in the ſubſequent ſtatute
and in common practiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 E. 3. 8. 5 E. 3. 9. 14 E. 3. 14.</note>The
Councell on the other ſide ſaid, that the ſtatute of 28 <hi>E.</hi> 3.
<hi>c.</hi> 3. expreſſeth and giveth life to this Charter, I ſhall
deſire to have that ſtatute read.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Keeling Clerk.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> whereas it is contained in the great Charter,
&amp;c. <hi>Vide</hi> all theſe ſtatutes following in Maſter
<hi>Littletons</hi> Argument in Parliament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Heath</hi> Atturney.</speaker>
               <p>My Lord, the reading of this ſtatute will give anſwer to it,
for it is apparent by the words thereof, none ſhall be taken by peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
&amp;c. and that the Court be extended to the firſt arreſt, but they are to
be underſtood that none ſhall be condemned, but hee ſhall be brought to
anſwer, and be tried.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:116495:31"/> And if it be expounded otherwiſe, it will
be contrary to that practiſe which was then in uſe.</p>
               <p>But it is utterly forbidden by this ſtatute, that any man
ſhould be condemned upon ſuggeſtions or petitions made to the King or
Councell, without due triall by Law.</p>
               <p>The next ſtatute they cited was 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi>
4. My Lord, I deſire that that may be read.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Keeling Clerk.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> that no man of what eſtate or condition ſoever
that he be, ſhall be put out of land or tenement, nor taken, nor
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, nor diſinherited, nor put to death, without being brought to
anſwer by due proceſſe of Law.<note place="margin">42 E. 3. 3.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Heath</hi> Atturney.</speaker>
               <p>My Lord, this ſtatute is intended to be a finall proſecution,
for if a man ſhall be impriſoned without due proceſſe, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be
brought to anſwer, that is unjuſt, and forbidden by this ſtatute; but
when a man is taken in cauſes that are unknown to us, (who walk below the
ſtaires) we are not privy to the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances which may cauſe the
triall to be delayed, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture it is not time to bring the matter to
triall, becauſe it is not yet come to maturity, and therefore this is not in
the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſtatute.</p>
               <p>Another ſtatute that they mention, is in the ſame year, and it
is <hi>pag.</hi> 9. <hi>chap.</hi> 9. I deſire it may be read.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Keeling Clerk.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> becauſe the people of the Realm, &amp;c.
<hi>Vide</hi> Maſter <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleton</hi> as before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Heath</hi> Atturney.</speaker>
               <p>My Lord, it is very clear, that this ſtatute had no manner of
thought of this cauſe in queſtion; But whereas Sheriffes did procure
Commiſſions to be awarded to themſelves for their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate 
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:116495:31"/> gain to the prejudice of the ſubject, the ſtatute
condemneth thoſe commiſſions, but it maketh nothing to this queſtion
which we have now in hand. The next ſtatute which they cited, was 37
<hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. I beſeech it may be read.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Keeling Clerk.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> though it be contained in the great Charter,
&amp;c. <hi>Vide</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Heath</hi> Atturney.</speaker>
               <p>My Lord, this ſtatute ſeems to be a commentary and light to
the other ſtatutes, the ſcope whereof is againſt private ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
made to the King or his Councell, and not in legall way, and therefore it
condemnes them; and this is more fully expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſtatute of 38
<hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. which they likewiſe mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by which
ſtatute direction is given what ſecurity thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which make
ſuch ſuggeſtions are to give, that they ſhould proſecute their
ſuggeſtions, and what puniſhment they ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe if their
ſuggeſtions be found falſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Keeling Clerk.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> as to the Article made at the laſt Parliament,
&amp;c. <hi>Vide</hi> as before ſaid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Heath</hi> Atturney.</speaker>
               <p>My Lord, this and the laſt ſtatute ſeem to conduce both to
one purpoſe, that they that in their accuſations went not in a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall way
to bring the party to his anſwer, it was directed by this ſtatute that they
ſhould goe a legall way.</p>
               <p>The laſt Parliament in print, the Councell on the other ſide
produced, was the ſtatute of 1 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 12. which I
deſire may be read.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Keeling Clerk.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> whereas divers people at the ſuit of parties were
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Fleet, &amp;c. <hi>Vide</hi> as before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:116495:32"/>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Heath</hi> Atturney.</speaker>
               <p>My Lord, it appeareth that the ſcope of this ſtatute is
againſt the Wardens of the Feet, for ſome miſcarriages in them; but there
is one thing in this ſtatute which I ſhall deſire your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to
obſerve: and that is, for thoſe miſdemeanours he ſhall forfeit his
office, except it be by writ from the King or his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, ſo that it
was no new doctrine in thoſe times, that the King might then give ſuch
commandment for committing: the ſcope of this ſtatute had two hands:
firſt, that the Warden ſhould forfeit his office: and ſecondly, that he
ſhould recompence the party.</p>
               <p>In the fourth and fifth of <hi>Phil. &amp; Mar. Dier</hi> 162. it
was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that if the Warden ſhall deliver a man out of priſon
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out command, hee forfeiteth his office and damage unto the party; But if
he have the command of the King, that ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the forfeiture of his
office, but he muſt bring the party hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and here theſe Gentlemen are
now, for that commandment of the King is no exception for him not to
obſerve.</p>
               <p>If he receives a writ from this Court, to ſhew the Court from
whence he receives his warrant, it may excuſe the forfeiture of his office,
but notwithſtanding he is ſubject to the action of the party.</p>
               <p>But I deſire your Lordſhip to obſerve that part of the
ſtatute, which the other party would not make uſe of, which is, that the
King may command by writ or otherwiſe; theſe were all the printed
ſtatutes cited by the Councell on the other ſide.</p>
               <p>But becauſe I would not miſinterpret theſe ſtatutes, I
thought it equall to deſire your Lordſhip that they might be read.</p>
               <p>Beſides the printed ſtatutes, they mentioned Petitions by the
Commons, and the Anſwers to them of ſeverall Kings in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The
firſt is, <hi>Rot. pl.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.
<hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Numero primo &amp; Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero viceſimo:</hi> beſides
theſe two, there is one other of 28 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:116495:32"/> My Lord, theſe three petitions and their
anſwers, the two firſt were mentioned by the Councell on the other ſide,
that in 28 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 28. I have produced all of them even to one
purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The Commons then petitioned the King, that all the Statutes made
in expoſition of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and of the Foreſt, may be kept and
obſerved: The King makes anſwer, that it ſhall be done. And in one of the
anſwers it is ſaid, If any man be grieved, he may complain. But what is all
this to the point in queſtion? could there be any other anſwer to give life
to theſe requeſts?</p>
               <p>The King he is petitioned that ſome are injured; he anſwers,
That if they complain they ſhall be relieved.</p>
               <p>And now my Lord we are where we were, to finde out the true
meaning of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> for there is the foundation of our Caſe,
all this that hath been ſaid concerneth other things, and nothing to the
thing in Queſtion.</p>
               <p>There is not a word either of the commitment of the King, or
commandment of the Councell in all the Statutes and Records.</p>
               <p>And now my Lord I am at an end of thoſe Statutes, and come to
that that was alledged and mentioned to be in 3 <hi>H.</hi> 6. 46. and if I
could have found it, I would have brought it, but I could not finde it,
therefore if they have it, I deſire that they will ſhew it, but I think
they have it not, and therefore I will let that goe.</p>
               <p>And now my Lord I come to that which I inſiſted upon, the
Queſtion as it was at firſt, not whether the King or the Lords of the
Councell can commit a man, and ſhew no cauſe wherefore they do commit him,
but whether the ordinary Courts of Juſtice have power to bail him or no; for
that I will inſiſt upon the Statute of <hi>Weſtm. primo,</hi> which I
deſire your Lordſhip may be read, and then I will apply.<note place="margin">Cap. 15. Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe Br. 11, 56, 78, Dier 170.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <p>
               <hi>Vide Weſtm. primo.</hi>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <p>My Lord, this Statute, if I miſunderſtand it not, is a full
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion <pb n="62" facs="tcp:116495:33"/> to this purpoſe of <hi>Magna
Charta,</hi> the ſcope whereof is to direct us in what caſe men
impriſoned were to be bailed.</p>
               <p>It was eſpecially for direction to the Sheriffes and others, but
to ſay Courts of Juſtice are excluded from this Statute, I conceive it
cannot be.</p>
               <p>It recites that whereas heretofore it was not reſolved in what
caſes men were repleviſable, and in what caſes not, but onely in theſe
four caſes, For the death of a man, or by the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King, or
of his Juſtices, or of the Foreſt.</p>
               <p>My Lord, I ſay that this Statute expreſſeth not the Law was
made by this Statute, that in theſe caſes men were not replevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable; but
it expreſſeth that the Law was clear in theſe caſes; In theſe four
caſes it was clearly reſolved before.</p>
               <p>I pray you, my Lord, obſerve the time of the making of this
Statute, that of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was made in the time of <hi>Henry</hi>
the third, and this of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in the time of <hi>Edward</hi>
the firſt, ſo that the firſt, it was made in the time of the ſame.</p>
               <p>And my Lord, if they had underſtood the Statute of <hi>Magna
Charta</hi> in another ſenſe, would they not have expreſſed it ſo in
this Statute? was it not fitter for them then for us, they being nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the
firſt making of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> then we are? But certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Statute
of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was expounded at the time as I have ſhewed before,
if not, without all doubt at the time of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Weſtm.
primo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Parliament would not have been ſo carefull to provide for
things of leſſer moment, and omit this of ſo great conſequence, if
there had been any queſtion of it. In all times and ages <hi>Magna
Charta</hi> hath been confirmed, but they ſhew not any one Law that doth
except againſt this poſitive Law of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the firſt,
or any Acts of Parliament; nay more, in any printed books, that in this caſe
men ſhould be repleviſable.</p>
               <p>My Lord, if you know nothing printed or unprinted, if any 
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:116495:33"/> will deſire to alter a courſe that always hath been
held, you will ſeek for preſidents, for the conſtant uſe and courſe
is the beſt expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Law; it is not enough for me to ſay, this
it is, unleſſe I make it good.</p>
               <p>Firſt then I ſay, they on the other ſide cannot cite one
Book, late Statute, or other thing, to prove, That they that have been
committed <hi>Per ſpeciale mandatum domini Regis,</hi> are bailable.</p>
               <p>But my Lord, I finde ſome to the contrary, that they are not
bailable, and I will cite ſome of them, and read of others, for I would not
in a caſe of that expectation, that it ſhould be thought that any thing
ſhould be miſ-interpreted.</p>
               <p>In the 33 of <hi>Hen.</hi> the ſixth, <hi>folio viceſimo
tertio, Robert Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> Caſe, he was committed <hi>Pro diverſis
cauſis ipſum dominum Regem tangent';</hi> this alters not the caſe, for
it was as good as no cauſe, for it was the Warrant <hi>Domini Regis,</hi> and
there is no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion upon this: But my Lord, I know this is not the point in
que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
               <p>The next thing I ſhall ſhew unto your Lordſhip, is
<hi>Paſch.</hi> 21 <hi>Edvardi primo, Rot. cla. ſecund.</hi> and this, my
Lord, was near the time of making of the Statute of <hi>Weſtm. prim.</hi> and
this preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent is to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The Sheriffe of <hi>Leiceſterſhire</hi> and
<hi>Warwickſhire,</hi> (for then there was but one Sheriffe to both thoſe
Shires) did receive commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Letters from the King; That whereas the
Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> had commanded divers perſons to the cuſtody of the
ſaid Sheriffe, the King ſent a Letter to the ſaid Sheriffe, commanding
that thoſe who were committed to his cuſtody by the Earl of
<hi>Warwick,</hi> he ſhould ſhew no grace to them, that is, they ſhould
not be bailed.</p>
               <p>The Sheriffe notwithſtanding this command lets ſome of thoſe
priſoners to bail, whereupon he was complained of in Parliament, that he had
done againſt the Kings commandement, and he was condemned for it.</p>
               <p>This was a Parliament, I wonder this ſhould be done in
Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that it was not ſaid there, That this commitment being 
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:116495:34"/> done by the Kings commandment was not good; no, he was
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in Parliament, for it was one that did break the Statute of
<hi>Weſtm. primo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lord, the uſe that I make of this Record is this, It recites,
that the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> committed divers, it might be that he did
commit them by direction from the King; but the Record menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth not ſo
much, but it ſhews, that the King by Letters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Sheriffe, that he
ſhould ſhew thoſe perſons no grace, and yet he did; he was examined
upon this, and by Parliament committed.</p>
               <p>The next matter I will offer to your Lordſhips judgement, for
the true expoſition of the Law in this caſe, is the Book we call the
<hi>Regiſter,</hi> an authority reſpected, it is the foundation of all our
Writs at the Common Law; I bring not the Book.<note place="margin">Regiſter
fol. 77, &amp;c.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In this Book there is one Writ ſaith thus, <hi>Rex, &amp;c. Quod
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plegiar' fac' A. niſi fuerit per ſpeciale mandatum domini
Regis.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtice <hi>Doderidge.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>In what Writ is that, <hi>De homine replegiando?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Atturney Generall.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, in the Writ <hi>De homine replegiando,</hi> and there is
another Writ directed to the Conſtable of <hi>Dover,</hi> in the very ſame
words; by which it appears, that they that are impriſoned by the Kings
command, <hi>non ſunt replegiabiles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">F.N.B. 66. f.</note>Maſter
<hi>Fitzherbert,</hi> a grave Judge, and is in authority with us, peruſing
theſe Writs, expreſſed it in theſe words plainly; There are ſome
caſes wherein a man cannot have this Writ, although he be taken and detained
in Priſon; as if he be taken by the death of a man, or if he be taken by the
commandement of the Kings Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and mentions not chief Juſtice, which
I beleeve is to be inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not of the chief of the Court of Judicature, but
of the chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of <hi>England,</hi> for there was ſuch a one in
thoſe days: Thus my Lord you ſee the opinion of Maſter
<hi>Fitzherbert</hi> in this caſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:116495:34"/> The next thing that I will ſhew your
Lordſhip, is the opinion of Maſter <hi>Stamford,</hi> in his Pleas of the
Crown, <hi>Fol.</hi> 72. where he ſets down the Statute of
<hi>Weſtminſter primo,</hi> and then he addes, That by this appears in four
caſes at the Common Law a man is not repleviſable, In thoſe that were
taken for the death of a man, or by the commandment of the King, or of his
Juſtices, or of the Foreſt: And there he ſaith, That the commandment of
the King is to be intended, either the commandment of his mouth, or of his
Councell, which is incorporated to him, and ſpeak with the mouth of the
King.</p>
               <p>My Lord, I ſhall deſire no better Commentaries upon a Law then
theſe reverent grave Judges, who have put books of Law in Print, and ſuch
Books as none, I beleeve, will ſay their judgements are weak.</p>
               <p>The next thing I ſhall offer unto your Lordſhip is this, that
I cannot ſhew with ſo great authority as I have done the reſt, becauſe
I have not the thing it ſelf by me; but I will put it to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips
memory, I preſume you may well remember it, It is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of all
the Judges, which was given in the four and thirti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of Queen
<hi>Elizabeth,</hi> it fell out upon an unhappy occaſion which was thus; The
Judges they complain that Sheriffes and other Officers could not execute the
proceſſe of the Law as they ought, for that the parties on whom ſuch
proceſſe ſhall be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted were ſent away by ſome of the Queens
Councell, that they could not be found; the Judges hereupon petitioned the Lord
Chancellor, that he would be a ſuitor to her Majeſty that nothing be done
hereafter. And thereupon the Judges were deſired to ſhew in what caſes
men that were committed were not bailable, whether upon the commitment of the
Queen or any other.</p>
               <p>The Judges make anſwer, That if a man ſhall be committed by
the Queen, by her command, or by the Privy Councell, he is not bailable: If
your Lordſhip ask me what authority I have for this, I can onely ſay, I
have it out of the Book of the Lord <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi> written with his own
hand.</p>
               <p>My Lord, I pray you give me leave to obſerve the time when 
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:116495:35"/> this was done; It was in a time, and we may truly call it
a good time, in the time of good Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and yet we ſee
there was then cauſe of complaint; and therefore I would not have men think
that we are now grown ſo bad (as the opinion is we are) for we ſee that
then in thoſe times there was cauſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and it may be more then
is now.</p>
               <p>This, my Lord, was the reſolution of all the Judges and Barons
of the Exchequer, and not by ſome great one.</p>
               <p>Now I will apply my ſelf to that which hath been enforced by the
Councell on the other ſide, which was the reaſon that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject hath
intereſt in this caſe.</p>
               <p>My Lord I do acknowledge it, but I muſt ſay that the Soveraign
hath great intereſt in it too. And ſure I am, that the firſt ſtone of
Soveraignty was no ſooner laid, but this power was given to the Soveraign; If
you ask me whether it be unlimited, my Lord, I ſay it is not the queſtion
now in hand: But the Common Law, which hath long flouriſhed under the
Government of our King and his Progenitors Kings of this Realm, have ever had
that reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent reſpect of their Soveraign, as that it hath concluded the King
can doe no wrong: And as it is in the Lord <hi>Berklies</hi> Caſe in
<hi>Plowdens Com.</hi> 246. <hi>b.</hi> it is part of the Kings Prerogative
that he can doe no wrong.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Title Travers 5.</note>In the fourth of
<hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, <hi>fol.</hi> 25. the King cannot be a
diſſeiſor; and ſo it is alſo in the Lord <hi>Berklies</hi> Caſe in
32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Dier fol.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>The King cannot uſurp upon a Patron, for the Common Law hath
that reverent reſpect to him, as that it cannot conceive he will doe any
injury.</p>
               <p>But the King commits a Subject, and expreſſeth no cauſe of
the commitment; what then? ſhall it be thought that there is no cauſe why
he ſhould be committed?</p>
               <p>Nay my Lord, the courſe of all times hath been, to ſay there
is no cauſe expreſſed, and therefore the matter is not ripe, and
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <pb n="67" facs="tcp:116495:35"/> upon the Courts of Judicature have ever
reſted ſatisfied there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, they would not ſearch into it.</p>
               <p>My Lords, there be <hi>Arcana Dei, &amp; Arcana Imperii,</hi> and
they that ſearch too farre into them, and make themſelves buſier with
them then their places do require, they will make themſelves &amp;c. I will
ſay no more; but I ſhall be able to ſhew that there ſhall as much
prejudice come to the Kingdome, if God direct not the heart of the King, which
is in the hand of God, as the Rivers of waters: I ſay there may as much
hazard come to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth in many other things, with which the King is
truſted, as in this particular there can accrew to the Subject.</p>
               <p>If a Treaſon be committed as it was not long agoe, nor farre
removed from our memories; ſince there was a Treaſon, and the Actors
thereof fled, ſome to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſome to
<hi>Brux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells,</hi> when it was to be put in execution; the Treaſon being
diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered one is apprehended upon ſuſpition of it, and is put into the
Tower, and there he lieth and thinketh the time very long, and I cannot blame
him.</p>
               <p>It may be he is innocent, and thereupon he brings a <hi>Habeas
Corpus,</hi> and by vertue of that Writ he is brought hither, and will your
Lordſhip think it fit or convenient to bail him, when the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation
againſt him muſt come from beyond the Sea? I think you will rather ſo
reſpect the proceedings of the State, as that you will beleeve theſe things
are done with a cauſe, then inquire further of them.</p>
               <p>Peradventure ſome great miſdemeanour may be committed, and
ſome of the parties make away, ſo as Proclamation cannot overtake them, and
ſome are taken, it is fit that they that are in priſon ſhould be tried
before the principall be taken.</p>
               <p>I will give you an inſtance, that lately was put into my minde;
There be ſome Priſoners in the Tower at this preſent, which were put in
thither when they were very young: If they ſhould bring an <hi>Habeas
Corpus,</hi> they were impriſoned for State matters, will <pb n="68" facs="tcp:116495:36"/> your-Lordſhip deliver them? No, in that the State doth not think it
fit to ſend them back into their own Countries. You will eſteem ſo
reverently of the State for committing children, that you will beleeve that
there is great reaſon of State ſo to doe, or elſe they would not doe it:
Many inconveniences may follow if it ſhould be otherwiſe. It may be divers
men doe ſuffer wrongfully in priſon, but therefore ſhall all priſoners
be delivered? that were a great miſchief.</p>
               <p>No doubt but the Kings Power is abſolute over his coins, if then
he ſhall command his coin ſhall be turned to braſſe or lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I
confeſſe it were inconvenient, but if the King would do it, the anſwer
that I can make is, that he would not undo the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; but can your
Lordſhip hinder it as being an inconvenience if he would doe it? the Cinque
Ports are free for traffique for all his Subjects, but the King in his Cabinet
underſtands there is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Warre to come upon this Kingdome, thereupon
he ſhuts the Ports that no man can goe out, ſhall the Merchant ſay this
is injuſtice in the King? And as in this, ſo in many other particulars this
may appear, but I will not goe too high: and therefore we are too wiſe, nay
we are too fooliſh, in undertaking to examine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of State, to which we
are not born. Now my Lord, I come to our Book caſes, by which it appears what
our King may doe, and nothing can be ſo againſt it, but he will not doe it;
the King may pardon all Traitors and felons, and if he ſhould doe it, may not
the Subjects ſay, If the King doe this, the bad will overcome the good? but
ſhall any ſay, the King cannot do this? no, we may onely ſay, he will not
doe this?</p>
               <p>The King may exempt men from the Office of Sheriffe, is not this
inconvenient? and may it not be ſaid, he may exempt ten in a Shire, and then
the burthen of the Country ſhall reſt upon the meaner ſort of people? can
any man ſay more to this, then that he will not do it?</p>
               <p>Inheritances are to be decided upon triall; the King may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt
private men from being of a Jury, but if he exempt all men, who ſhall try our
Cauſes? for it is to be preſumed, that he will not doe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:116495:36"/> But to our Caſe; by the Statute of
<hi>Magna Charta,</hi> no man ſhall be put out of his free-hold, &amp;c. But
if the King will doe it, muſt not the party that is ſo put out goe to the
King by Petition? But you will ſay, it is a Petition of Right, and it may be
theſe gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemens is ſo; admit it be, yet when ſuch a Petition comes to
the King, muſt it not be anſwered with theſe words, <hi>Soit droit fait
al parte?</hi> and when that the King will give that Warrant for it, then they
muſt have it done, and not before.</p>
               <p>And this may anſwer a perpetuall impriſonment, and God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
that this ſhould be ſo: And now my Lord, I will trouble you no longer, but
I will goe to preſidents. Preſidents I know prevail much, and rule in many
caſes, and if the preſidents they cite were not miſ-interpreted, I
ſhould think they had ſaid a great deal.</p>
               <p>But my Lord, I will anſwer their preſidens with preſidents;
nay, I will ſhew your Lordſhip that the preſidents which they have ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
are no preſidents for them.</p>
               <p>And my Lord, it is a dangerous thing for men in matters of weight
to avouch preſidents with confidence, when they make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for them: for
my Lord, preſidents are now become almoſt Proclamations, for they already
run up and down the Town, and yet they know but part of them, and not all, and
I think if they knew all, men would be more modeſt.</p>
               <p>But my Lord, I will now come to theſe preſidents, where I may
ſay they have not dealt freely with me, for they have ſhewed me many
preſidents more then they mentioned here, and it may be they have done the
like unto your Lordſhip.</p>
               <p>They alledged but eight preſidents before your Lordſhip, but
they have brought ſixteen unto me: for theſe eight mentioned here, I will
take them in order as they were cited, and anſwer.</p>
               <p>The firſt preſident they cited was in <hi>Henry</hi> the
eight, <hi>Rot.</hi> 9. one <hi>Harriſon,</hi> we have the Record here to
ſhew your Lordſhip, <pb n="70" facs="tcp:116495:37"/> that he was committed for
ſuſpition of felony, which was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Warrant; and then my
Lord, this is clear, if the King, or the Lords of the Councell, will
expreſſe any thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Lordſhips juriſdiction, there is good
ground for your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings: But when there is nothing expreſſed, whether
you will judge what the cauſe of the Warrant is, I will leave to your
Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips judgement, but it appears this was the cauſe, and that he was
delivered.</p>
               <p>The next preſident was 22 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Rot.</hi> 57. and
it was <hi>Parkers</hi> caſe; and it is true that his commitment appeared to
be <hi>Per ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciale mandatum domini Regis,</hi> but it was alſo propoſed
to bee <hi>Pro pace &amp; ſuſpicione feloniae;</hi> and the ſignification
of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was given by Maſter <hi>Peck</hi> of <hi>Cliffords Inne;</hi>
but there the Warrant ſhews the cauſe of the commitment was for the peace
and ſuſpition of felony, and therefore he was bailed.</p>
               <p>The next was in 40 <hi>Eliz. Wendons</hi> Caſe; but my Lord,
that commitment was out of the Star-chamber by an ordinary courſe: Then they
cited 8 <hi>Jac. Thomas Caeſars</hi> Caſe, he indeed was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by
<hi>Speciale mandatum domini Regis,</hi> and brought his <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas
Corpus,</hi> but the Roll ſaith <hi>remittitur;</hi> and is that a Warrant
for them to ſay that he was delivered?</p>
               <p>Then Sir <hi>Thomas Vernons</hi> Caſe was cited; and my Lord
when we looked into the Records we found that he was committed for
ſuſpition of Treaſon; and he was tried for it and diſcharged.</p>
               <p>The next preſident was Sir <hi>Thomas Monſons</hi> Caſe; I
wonder that they did cite that, for he was committed by the Lords of the
Councell indeed, but the ground of it was the ſuſpition of the death of Sir
<hi>Thomas Overbury,</hi> and he was diſcharged again by the Lords of the
Councell. Certainly if you had known this, you would not have named this as a
preſident for you.</p>
               <p>The next was <hi>Reynors</hi> Caſe; he my Lord, was one of the
Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder-Treaſon, and yet there was a Warrant to diſcharge him too. And
therefore what theſe preſidents are, I ſhall ſubmit to 
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:116495:37"/> your Lordſhip, I muſt confeſſe when they are cited
together, they make a great noiſe, but when they are examined ſeverally
they prove nothing.</p>
               <p>My Lord, there is one more preſident of theſe that were cited
here before your Lordſhip, and I hope that one ſhall be as none.</p>
               <p>It was mentioned to be <hi>Lawrence Browns</hi> Caſe, 30
<hi>Eliz.</hi> I know not what it is, but it is like to be of the ſame value
as the reſt, <hi>Pro certis cauſis eos moventibus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus, my Lord, I have gone through thoſe preſidents that
were alledged here before your Lordſhip; and now I will come to theſe
preſidents that were brought to me, and not mentioned here.</p>
               <p>The firſt was <hi>John Brownings</hi> Caſe, in 21 <hi>H.</hi>
8. My Lord, theſe preſidents came not to me before Saturday laſt about
candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting, and yeſterday was no time fitting to ſearch out
preſidents, and how could I then ſearch for this?</p>
               <p>The next was <hi>William Rogers</hi> Caſe of the ſame time.
But the cauſe is expreſſed to be for ſuſpition of felony, which is a
cauſe within the Juriſdiction of this Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Newports</hi> Caſe was the like in 4 <hi>&amp;</hi> 5
<hi>Phil. &amp; Mar.</hi> and ſo was <hi>Thomas Lawrence</hi> Caſe, 9
<hi>Eliz.</hi> and <hi>Edw. Harecourts</hi> Caſe, 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> which was
for ſuſpition of felony. <hi>Richard Beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,</hi> and not
<hi>Barkwith</hi> as was cited, for they have miſtaken both names and
matters, was committed <hi>Per ſpeciale mandatum domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Regis;</hi> and the
Record ſaith he was bailed. But it was by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a letter from the
Lords of the Councell.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of <hi>Peter mans</hi> commitment in the 4 and 5 of
<hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> appears to be for ſuſpition of felony
and robbery.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Reynors</hi> caſe it is the ſame with
<hi>Beckwith,</hi> and were both for one thing.</p>
               <p>In the eighth of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, one <hi>Rog:
Cherry</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <pb n="72" facs="tcp:116495:38"/> 
                  <hi>Per mandatum domini
Regis,</hi> and it was for a criminall caſe, and he was afterwards indicted
and acquited and delivered.</p>
               <p>And there is another preſident thereof, that ſaith, he was
after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards arraigned, condemned, and hanged, we have the Record of it.</p>
               <p>And now my Lord, I will ſhew ſome preſidents on the other
ſide, where men have been committed by the commandement of the King, and by
the commandement of the Councell, and have been delivered again by their
directions: And of this kinde there be two in the Tower, that as they were
committed by Warrant, ſo by Warrants again for their bailing they were
delivered; the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences were againſt the Foreſt and for Murther.</p>
               <p>In the fourth of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, <hi>M.</hi> 4.
<hi>Edmond de Newport</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> was indicted for an offence
committed by him in the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. And <hi>M.</hi> 7. <hi>John Fox</hi> was
likewiſe indicted for an offence by him done in the Foreſt: and there be
two Warrants to bail them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M.</hi> 20. <hi>John Cobb</hi> was the like, and there was a
letter from the King, <hi>Quod ponatur in Ballium uſque ad proximam
Aſsiſam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe were offences within <hi>Weſtminſter primo,</hi> and
there be ſeverall Warrants to bail them.</p>
               <p>The Clark of this Court hath many Records, by which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth,
that many have been committed by the command of the King and of the Queen, and
of the Councell, and brought their <hi>Habeas Corpus;</hi> and the
ſucceſſe was, that many of them were committed to the ſame Priſons,
and divers were committed to the Marſhall of this Court; the reaſon was,
for that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them were to appear here, their cauſes being triable here,
and it would have been a great trouble to ſend them back ſo farre to
Priſon as into the Countries, and therefore they were delivered to the
Marſhall of the Kings Houſhold: again, many had their Trials in this Court,
and ſome ſuffered, and ſome were delivered by ſpeciall command as they
were committed by ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:116495:38"/> The number of theſe of this nature are
infinite that have been in our times, we have found ſome forty preſidents
of men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted out of the Chancery, and by the High Commiſſion, for
contempts, and ſome by the Barons of the Exchequer, and ſome in
<hi>London</hi> that have been brought hither by <hi>Habeas corpus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of this I ſhall obſerve, that in the 11 <hi>Iacobi,</hi> there
was a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conſtitution in <hi>London</hi> made between the white Bakers,
that they might live one by another, and the one not to invade the others
liberties, and for contempt againſt this Ordinance, ſome were committed to
priſon, as <hi>Thomas Heanning,</hi> and <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlepage,</hi> they had a
<hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> and the cauſe was ſhewn to be by reaſon of the
ſaid Conſtitution, and thereupon the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were ſent back to
<hi>London</hi> to abide the Order of the Mayor; for my Lord, this Court hath
been ever carefull not to examine the Decrees of the Chancery, or Court of
Requeſts, but have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looked whether the cauſe returned be within the
juriſdiction of this Court nor have they called in queſtion the by-laws and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of <hi>London,</hi> but they ſend them back to the court of
Juſtice that committeth them.</p>
               <p>And hath this Court been ſo carefull of theſe inferiour Courts
to this which is the chief, and when the King who is the head of Juſtice
ſhall commit a man, ſhall not they be as carefull to do the like Juſtice
to them? But when the King ſaith to them, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment was by my warrant
and commandment, will you queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this? and whether this commitment be good
or no? I hope you will not.</p>
               <p>And now my Lords, touching ſome preſidents which have been
taken out of their own ſhewing, I ſhall make it appear, that as they have
been committed by the King or Councel, ſo they had warrants alſo to
diſcharge them: and they my Lords, are two ancient Records, the firſt is 7
<hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Rot.</hi> 6. the other <hi>Rot.</hi> 73. the firſt was
<hi>Thomas Brown,</hi> he was committed to the Marſhalſeys, <hi>Per
mandatum domini Regis, &amp; aliis certis de cauſis:</hi> and afterwards the
Records ſay, <hi>Dominus Rex quoad Chaſe relaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit mandatum ſuum,</hi>
and he was bailed and the reſt lay by it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:116495:39"/> My Lords, I will conclude, I could be
infinite in this caſe in preſidents, but enough is enough, your Lordſhip
knoweth the weight of preſidents, it is not enough to ſhew this was done,
but alſo to ſhew the reaſon why it was done: I wil trouble your
Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip no longer, but if any man ſhall doubt whether that or any part
thereof, be truly recited, which hath been ſaid touching the Records or
Statutes, I can ſay no more but that the ſtatutes have been read, and the
Records are ready ſorted out to be ſeen by your Lordſhip.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude (that I ſhall ſay) in this caſe to
anſwer the fear rather then the juſt ground, of them that ſay that this
may be a cauſe of great danger, with the words of <hi>Bracton,</hi> who
ſpake not to flatter the preſent age, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> 8. in
the end, ſpeaking of a writ for wrong done by the King to the Subject
touching land, he ſaith theſe words, <hi>ſi judicium à Rege
teſtatur (cum breve non currat contra ipſum) locus erat ſupplicationi
quod factum ſuum corrigat &amp; emendet, quod quidem ſi non fecerit ſatis
ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit ei ad poenam quod dominum expectet ultorem, nemo qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem de factis
ſuis praeſumat diſputare, multo fortius contra fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ſuum
venire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lords, I engliſhed it not, for I apply it not, any man may
make uſe of it as he pleaſeth; and ſo I conclude both for the point of
Exception, and matter of the Return, which I referre to your Lordſhips
judgement, whether all in the Return but theſe words <hi>Per ſpeciale
mandatum domini Regis,</hi> be not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous. And for the matter, whether
theſe Gentlemen be bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable or not bailable, I have ſhewed your
Lordſhip, that by the practiſe of all ages they are not bailable, but have
beene remaunded back.</p>
               <p>And therefore I pray your Lordſhip, that theſe Gentlemen may
be remitted, and left to goe the right way for their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is by
Petition to the King: whether it be a Petition of right or of grace I know not;
it muſt be I am ſure to the King, from whom I do perſonally underſtand
that theſe Gentlemen did never yet preſent any Petition to him that came to
his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:116495:39"/>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Hide</hi> Chief Juſtice.</speaker>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Atturney,</hi> thus much we muſt ſay to you, you
have taken a great deal of pains, you having had ſo ſhort a time to
conſider of this caſe, it is a caſe of very grear weight and expectation,
and we doe not intend that you ſhall expect long for our reſolution, for
that theſe Gentlemen are in priſon, and deſire no doubt to know where
they muſt truſt; I hope we ſhall reſolve according to the reaſon of
former times, and according to our conſciences: but this I muſt tell you,
as I did thoſe that argued, you muſt bring in your preſidents, for though
wee have ſeen ſome of them, yet ſome of them we have not ſeen,
therefore we deſire that your ſervants or your ſelves doe attend, and
bring unto us after dinner, thoſe preſidents you have mentioned on the
Kings part, for we intend to meet this afternoon, and you ſhall have our
opinions to morrow: and I muſt tell you on the other ſide, that this
cauſe being of ſuch weight, Councell ſhould be wary, how they ſpeak
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to inveagle the Court.</p>
               <p>Touching ſuch preſidents as you urged in ſome of them, we
know there is ſomething urged which makes not for you, ſo you have omitted
ſome materiall things to be ſhewn; I ſpeake it to this purpoſe, not to
prejudice the cauſe or to deliver my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, which becomes me not, but to
ſhew, that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors ſhould be carefull, and this I dare ſay, there
is matter in ſome of the preſidents themſelves that leads to another
caſe if they were intirely cited.</p>
               <p>The Term grows away, you ſhall not be long in expectation, we
will meet this afternoon, and give you our opinions to morrow morning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:116495:40"/>
               <speaker>Maſter <hi>Noye.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>We deſire that Maſter <hi>Atturney</hi> may bring the
preſidents of 34 <hi>Elizabeth</hi> with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Maſter Atturney.</speaker>
               <p>I will ſhew you any thing, but my Lord, I ſhal be bold to
claim the priviledge of my place, as the Kings Councell, when the Kings
Atturney hath ſpoken, there ought to be no Arguments after that, but if you
aske to ſee any thing you ſhall have it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Hide</hi> Chief Juſtice.</speaker>
               <p>It is that we aim at, the truth and right may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and not
ſatisfie the one or the other part, but it is not deſired to make uſe of
it by way of reply, but for ſatisfaction onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serjeant <hi>Bramſtone.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My Lord, for the preſidents I cited, I did think they ſhould
have been brought and read in the Court that your Lordſhip might ſee
them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Hide</hi> Chiefe Iuſtice.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhall need no Apology, the Records and Preſidents ſhall
be brought to the Court, and read openly, for the Court will not wrong you, and
you ſhall ſee the difference between them, and your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them, nor
you muſt not wrong us with your written verities.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>On thurſday the twenty eight of <hi>November, Michaelis</hi> 3.
<hi>Caroli Regis, Hide</hi> Chief Juſtice, Juſtice <hi>Doderidge,</hi>
Juſtice <hi>Jones,</hi> and Juſtice <hi>Whitlock</hi> on the Bench: Sir
<hi>John Corbet,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Earle,</hi> Sir <hi>John Henningham,</hi>
and Sir <hi>Edmund Hampden</hi> at the Bar.</head>
            <sp>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:116495:40"/>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Hide</hi> Chief Iuſtice.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſure you here expect the reſolution of the whole Court,
as accordingly yeſterday we told you you ſhould have.</p>
               <p>This is a caſe of very great weight and great expectation, and
it had been fit we ſhould have uſed more ſolemn arguments of it then now
for the ſhortneſſe of the time we can doe, for you have been long in
priſon, and it is fit you ſhould know where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you ſhould truſt: I am
ſure you expect Juſtice from hence, and God forbid we ſhould ſit here
but to doe Juſtice to all men according to our beſt skill and knowledge,
for it is our oaths and duties ſo to doe, and I am ſure there is nothing
elſe expected of us. We are ſworn to maintain all the Prerogatives of the
King, that is one branch of our oath, and we are likewiſe ſworn to
adminiſter Juſtice equally to all people.</p>
               <p>We cannot I tell you deliver in ſolemn arguments and give the
judgements of every one of us touching this caſe, as the weight thereof
requireth; but we have met together, and we have duly and ſeriouſly
conſidered of it, and of all that which hath been ſpoken of on either
ſide, and we are grown to a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and my brothers have injoined me
to del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver to you, the reſolution
of the whole Court: and therefore though it bee delivered by my mouth, it is
the reſolution of us all: I hope I ſhall not miſtake any thing of their
intention in my delivery, but if I doe they ſit here by me, and I ſhall not
take it ill if they right me.</p>
               <p>Therefore I muſt tell you there hath been many points learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly
argued at the Bar, which we ſhall not touch, or give our reſolution upon,
but bend our ſelves to the point in judgement here.</p>
               <p>Theſe three Statutes, as for example, the ſtatute of <hi>Magna
Charta,</hi> 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. and 36 <hi>E.</hi> 3. and the ſtatute of
<hi>Weſtminſter primo,</hi> &amp; divers other ſtatutes that have been
alledged, &amp; particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly <pb n="78" facs="tcp:116495:41"/> diſputed of, we all
acknowledge and reſolve, that they are good Laws, and that they be in force,
but the interpretation of them at this time belongs not to us, for we are
driven to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother point: and though the meaning of them belongs to the one way
or the other, yet our judgement muſt be the ſame; for that which is now to
be judged by us is this, whether one that is committed by the Kings authority,
and no cauſe declared of his commitment, according as here it is upon this
return, whether we ought to deliver him by bail, or to remaund him back againe?
Wherein you muſt know this which your Councell will tell you, we can take
notice onely of this return, and when the caſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to come to us no
otherwiſe then by the return, wee are not bound to examine the truth of the
return, but the ſufficiency of it, for there is a great difference between
the ſufficiency and the truth.</p>
               <p>We cannot judge upon rumours nor reports, but upon that which is
before us on record, and therefore the Return is exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable by us whether it
be ſufficient or not.</p>
               <p>The exceptions which have been taken to this Return were two: the
one for the form, the other for the ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>For the form, whether it be formally returned or no, for it is not
returned (as it is ſaid) poſitively and abſolutely, that they were
committed by the King, but as it appears by a warrant from the Lords of the
Councell, and then there ſeems to bee a contradiction in the return.</p>
               <p>For firſt it ſaith, they were committed by the Kings command,
and afterwards it alledgeth it to be by a warrant of the Lords of the Councell,
and ſo it is repugnant.</p>
               <p>Now we conceive that this is a poſitive and an abſolute
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, and ſo the reaſon is, that he firſt returns that they are
detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the ſpeciall command of the King, and if he had ceaſed there,
it had been poſitive; now there follows that this was ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to them by
the Lords of the Councell, this is returned to <pb n="79" facs="tcp:116495:41"/> aſcertain
the Court that he returned the cauſe truly, and to ſhew us that we ſhould
not doubt the verity of this return, &amp; not to ſhew to us that he hath no
knowledge of the cauſe but by the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords of the
Councell, according to that caſe of the Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi>
touching the excommunication, he muſt teſtifie his own knowledge, and not
<hi>continetur in Archivis:</hi> ſo a Sheriffe muſt not return <hi>quod
mandavi ball' &amp;c.</hi> and he gives this anſwer, unleſſe it be the
Bailiffe of a Liberty that hath return of writs.</p>
               <p>And ſo here if the Warden of the Fleet had returned that the
Lords of the Councell had ſignified unto him that his priſoner was detained
by the Kings commandment, that had been ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient: but when he returns
poſitively, at the firſt that is done by the Kings direction, hee ſhews
afterwards that which ſhould make it appear that he deals not falſly, which
might have been omitted, but being mentioned that that is the ſcope of it,
and not otherwiſe, the return is good and poſitive.</p>
               <p>Now then to the other objections, becauſe he ſpeaks nothing of
the caption why they were taken, you know it is the uſuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of all
Officers to anſwer the point in queſtion; there is not one word in the Writ
that demands the cauſe why they were taken, but why they are detained: ſo
that the point in the Writ is ſufficiently anſwered; for though ſometimes
it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that the cauſe of the caption ſhould be certified, yet
ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is ſuperfluous, but in our caſe the cauſe of the
detention is ſufficiently anſwered, which is the demand of the Writ, and
therefore we reſolve that the form of this Return is good. The next thing, is
the maine point in Law, whether the ſubſtance or matter of the Return be
good or no, wherein the ſubſtance is this, he doth certifie that they are
detained in priſon by the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall command of the King, and whether this
be good in Law or no, that is the queſtion.</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe if you remember this point, I ſay you did not
cite any Book or Caſe in print but many preſidents, which I confeſſe
are as ſtrong as any Book Caſes; for Book Caſes I <pb n="80" facs="tcp:116495:42"/>
confeſſe are taken and ſelected out of the Records and Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of
Judges, and that is it which is in our Books, though they be not ſo obvious
for every eye, but are found out by pains and diligent ſearch, and being
produced are of the ſame and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall authority with our Book Caſes, but
this muſt be when Records are brought faithfully and entirely, ſo that the
Court may adjudge of them.</p>
               <p>Now the preſidents you urged them to be ſo many, and ſo
fully to the point, that wee may thereby ſee that it is good to hear what can
be ſaid on both ſides, and for to heare all, and view the Records
themſelves, and therefore we required you to bring the Records to us, and you
did ſo, and you brought us more then you mentioned here; and we have
peruſed them all, that thereby we might ſee whether the Court be faithfully
dealt withall or no, for though Counſellors may urge a Book for their own
advantage, yet it is the duty of the Court to ſee and diſtinguiſh of
their allegations, as the truth may appear.</p>
               <p>This I told you yeſterday, when I told you your preſidents
warranted not ſo much as you urge them for; for if you be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred you urge
ſome preſidents to be, that where men were committed by the King, or by the
Lords of the Councell, and no cauſe expreſſed why they were committed,
they were delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>This is in effect our caſe, if the preſidents affirm that when
a man is committed by the Kings command, and no juſt cauſe is ſhewn, that
upon ſuch a generall Return the party ſhall <hi>ipſo facto</hi> be
delivered, for if the Return be not amended that he ſhall be
diſcharged.</p>
               <p>For although men come with prepared minds, yet the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of
every mans heart ought to ſubmit to the truth, and by the preſidents, you
ſhall ſee if it be ſo as you have alledged; but this I dare affirm, that
no one of the Records that you have ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, doth inforce what you have
concluded out of them, no not one; and therefore as you have cited Records and
Preſidents, Preſidents ſhall judge this caſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:116495:42"/> I will ſhew you how they differ from the
Records, you have concluded when the King hath committed one, and
expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not the cauſe, the Court hath delivered the party; but you
ſhall ſee the contrary concluded in every Caſe that you have put, where
the cauſe of the commitment hath been expreſſed, there the party hath
been delivered by the Court, if the Caſe ſo requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but where there hath
been no cauſe expreſſed, they have ever been remaunded, or if they have
been delivered, they have been delivered by the Kings direction, or by the
Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: If this fall now in proof, you ſee you have gathered
fair con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions out of the Records, and that you may ſee that this is
ſo, I have brought the Records with me of your own propounding, and I will
goe through them from point to point, and then judge your ſelves of the
caſe.</p>
               <p>It is not materiall whether I call for them in that order as you
produced them or no, and therefore I will take them as they are, firſt or
laſt in the Kings Reign; They are in number many, in the time of
<hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, Queen <hi>Mary,</hi>
Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> his time.</p>
               <p>I will ſhew you Sir <hi>Thomas Monſons</hi> Caſe in 14
<hi>Iacobi</hi> which was in all our memories.</p>
               <p>I will begin with <hi>Paſche,</hi> in 8 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Roger
Cherries</hi> Caſe, you vouched it to this purpoſe, That <hi>Cherry</hi>
being committed by the Major of <hi>Windſor,</hi> was brought hither by a
<hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> and the Major he returns that he was committed <hi>Per
mandatum domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Regis,</hi> and that thereupon he was delivered; but you
ſhall find by the Record that he was committed by the Major at the ſuit of
the King for felony, for which he was afterwards indicted, brought to a triall,
and then diſcharged.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vide</hi> this Record in Maſter <hi>Seldens</hi> Argument in
the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 3 <hi>&amp;</hi> 4 <hi>Caroli Regis,</hi> and ſo all the
reſt after mentioned.</p>
               <p>The next was 19 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Vrſwicks</hi> Caſe; and you
ſay he was brought hither by the Warden of the <hi>Fleet,</hi> who as you
ſaid, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned <pb n="82" facs="tcp:116495:43"/> that he was committed <hi>Per mandatum
domini Regis,</hi> and you ſaid he was diſcharged, but he was bailed upon
the Lords Letter, and brought hither to record his return, for he was bound to
appear here, and then he was diſcharged; but that was the cauſe of his
bringing hither, <hi>vide</hi> the Records as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>The next was <hi>Hugh Pains</hi> Caſe, in 21 <hi>H.</hi> 7. and
that you ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thus, you ſay that he was brought hither by a <hi>Habeas
Corpus,</hi> by the Warden of the <hi>Fleet,</hi> who returned that he was
committed by the Kings Councell, and he was bailed: Now we finde that he was
committed by them for ſuſpition of felony; and that cauſe was declared,
and he was bailed; ſo that you ſee there was a cauſe expreſſed.
<hi>Vide</hi> the Record aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>The next is 2 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Thomas Beckley</hi> and
<hi>Robert Harriſons</hi> Caſe; theſe you ſaid were brought in hither
by <hi>George</hi> Earle of <hi>Shrewſbury,</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of
<hi>Surrey;</hi> and the Return was, that they were committed by the command of
<hi>Hen.</hi> 7. and that they were bailed; but you ſhall finde that they
were committed for ſuſpition of felony; and that <hi>Harriſon</hi> was
committed by <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. but it was for Homicide upon the Sea, and ſo
the cauſe is expreſſed, and afterwards he was bailed. The next was in 22
<hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>John Parkers</hi> Caſe; you urged it to this purpoſe,
That he was brought hither by a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> by the Sheriffs of
<hi>London,</hi> and they you ſaid returned, that he was committed <hi>Per
ſpeciale man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum domini Regis nunciatum, &amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Robert Peck,
&amp;c.</hi> the cauſe why you urged this was twofold; firſt, that he was
commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Kings command, and yet he was bailed: ſecondly, that he was
committed <hi>Per mandatum domini Regis nunciat' per</hi> ſuch a one: But you
ſhall finde by the Record that he was committed for the ſecurity of peace,
and for ſuſpition of felony, and that was the cauſe for which he was
bailed, for he is bailable by Law when ſuch a cauſe appears. <hi>Vide</hi>
the Record as afore.</p>
               <p>Goe on to the next, and that is <hi>Peter Mans</hi> Caſe in the
3 &amp; 4 <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> you urged that to this purpoſe,
You ſay, that he was brought by the Keeper of the <hi>Gatehouſe,</hi> and
you ſay, that <pb n="83" facs="tcp:116495:43"/> he returned, that he was committed by the
command of the King and the Queens Councell, and thereupon he was bailed; but
you ſhall finde that he was committed for ſuſpition of felony and
robbery, and thereupon he was bailed.</p>
               <p>The next is in the 4 &amp; 5 <hi>Phil. &amp; Mar. Edward
Newports</hi> Caſe; you ſaid that the Conſtable of the <hi>Tower</hi>
brought him hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and returned that he was committed by the Councell of the
King and the Queen, and that he was bailed, but you ſee the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords that he
was committed for ſuſpition of coyning, which is bailable onely in this
Court, and therefore it was removed hither; yet this I muſt tell you, that it
is true in one Record, it appears not but as you have cited it; but you may
ſee how it is ſupplied by another Record, and the cauſe, and he was
delivered by a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation. <hi>Vide</hi> both Records in Maſter
<hi>Seldens</hi> Argument, as aforeſaid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doderidge.</speaker>
               <p>He could not be delivered by Proclamation unleſſe it was for a
criminall cauſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Hide</hi> Chief Iuſtice.</speaker>
               <p>Obſerve another thing in the Book, he is brought hither by the
ſpeciall command of the Councell, ſo that although it appears not in the
Record, yet if the King or Lords mean to have him tried for his life, he is
brought hither: Then you cited <hi>Robert Conſtables</hi> caſe, 9
<hi>Eliz.</hi> and you ſaid he was brought hither by the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the
Tower, who returned that he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Lords of the Councell, and
thereupon he was bailed; but you ſhall finde that he came hither to plead his
pardon, and he was pardoned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vide</hi> the Record as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Laurence</hi> Caſe in 9 <hi>Eliz.</hi> is the ſame
with <hi>Conſtables,</hi> for it appears that he was brought hither to 
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:116495:44"/> plead his pardon, and he was pardoned, and that was the
cauſe he was brought hither.</p>
               <p>The next was in 21 <hi>Eliz. John Brownings</hi> caſe; it is
true he was committed by the Lords of the Councell, and he was brought by a
<hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> to the chamber of Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Wray,</hi> Chief
Juſtice, and he was there bailed.</p>
               <p>The next was 33 <hi>Eliz. William Rogers;</hi> and he you ſaid
was brought hither by the Keeper of the <hi>Gatehouſe,</hi> who returned,
that he was committed to him by the Lords of the Councell, yet there was a
cauſe expreſſed, and that was for ſuſpition of coining of money.</p>
               <p>The next was in 39 <hi>Eliz. Lawrence Brown,</hi> you ſay that
he was brought hither by the Keeper of the <hi>Gate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi> who returned
that he was committed for divers cauſes, moving the Lords of the Councell,
and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he was delivered; but the Record is, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn alſo was
for ſuſpition of Treaſon, and although the ſuſpition of Treaſon
appears not in one Record, yet there is another for it: Here you ſee cauſe
of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment, and that he was bailed, but it was by the Kings command,
<hi>Vſque Octabis Michaelis, vide</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</p>
               <p>I blame not you that are of Councell with theſe Gentlemen for
urging this Record, for this Cauſe is not expreſſed in your Record, but
that he was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by command of the Councell onely, but he was committed
for ſuſpition of felony with Sir <hi>Thomas Smith: Vide</hi> the
Record.</p>
               <p>The next is in 40 <hi>Eliz. Edward Harecourts</hi> Caſe, and
<hi>Thomas Wendens</hi> Caſe; I bring them together becauſe they are both
in one year; in the 40 of <hi>Eliz. Edward <pb n="85" facs="tcp:116495:44"/> Harecourt</hi>
you ſay was committed to the <hi>Gatehouſe</hi> by the Lords of the
Councell, and the Return was that he was committed by them <hi>Certis de
cauſis ipſos moventibus ignotis,</hi> and he was bailed.</p>
               <p>Here is another in the ſame time committed to the ſame
priſon by the Lords in the Star-chamber, it was <hi>Thomas Wendens</hi>
caſe, and he you ſay was committed by them <hi>Certis de cauſis,</hi> (as
the other was) and that he was bailed; but you ſhall finde in the margin of
the Roll, <hi>Traditur in ball' ex aſſenſu Concilii dominae Reginae;</hi>
and that was the relation of the Queens Atturney, ſo that you ſee how that
preſident fits you.</p>
               <p>The next are two more of the <hi>Gatehouſe, Beckwith</hi> and
<hi>Reyner,</hi> they, you ſaid, were committed to the <hi>Gate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi>
brought their <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> and the Keeper of the
<hi>Gatehouſe</hi> returned, that they were committed by vertue of a Warrant
from the Archibiſhop of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Henry</hi> Earl of
<hi>Northampton,</hi> Lord Warden of the Cinque Ports, and others of the Privy
Councell, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring the ſaid Keeper to receive the ſaid <hi>Beckwith</hi>
and <hi>Reyner</hi> into his charge, untill they ſhould have further order
from them in that behalf; and you ſay they were bailed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vide</hi> the Record in Maſter <hi>Seldens</hi>
aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Now you ſhall ſee the direction to bail him; he was bailed by
the direction from the Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, as appears by their Letter.
<hi>Vide</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Now we come to <hi>Caeſars</hi> Caſe in 8 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> you
urged that to this purpoſe; you ſay he was committed to the
<hi>Marſhalſey,</hi> who upon a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> returned, That he
was committed <hi>Per ſpeciale mandatum domini Regis,</hi> and you ſay,
becauſe the Return was ſo generall, the <pb n="86" facs="tcp:116495:45"/> rule of the
Court was, that it ſhould be amended, or elſe he ſhould be diſcharged,
I will open to you what the reaſon of that rule was, for that notice was
taken, that the Keeper of the Priſon had uſed a falſe Return, and had
uſurped the name of the King, I know not how, but the commitment was not by
the Kings command; and that was the cauſe that he had day given him to amend
his Return, but his body was remaunded to Priſon, as you ſhall ſee the
Record. <hi>Vide</hi> the Record, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The laſt preſident that you uſed, was that of Sir
<hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Monſon,</hi> and that was ſo notorious, and ſo late, that I
marvell that was offered at all, it made me jealous of all the reſt, that was
ſo notorious; and now I have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted none you brought me. <hi>Vide</hi> the
Record.</p>
               <p>By this Record you may ſee that he was committed by divers Lords
of the Councell, and it was for the ſuſpition of the death of Sir
<hi>Thomas Overbury;</hi> and it is notoriouſly known, that he was brought
hither to plead his pardon.</p>
               <p>I will not tell you that you read all theſe preſidents, for
you read none, but urged them here before us, but we required you to bring them
to us, and they were brought to us, Maſter <hi>Corbet</hi> brought them all
but one, and that Maſter <hi>Noye</hi> brought, it was in 22 <hi>H.</hi> 8.
<hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> Caſe: And one Maſter <hi>Holborn</hi> a man whoſe face
I never ſaw before, nor is he now in mine eye, did ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday bring us one
preſident to this purpoſe, and it was Sir <hi>John Brockets</hi> Caſe in
1 <hi>Jac.</hi> he was committed to the <hi>Gatehouſe,</hi> and upon a
<hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> the Keeper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned that <hi>Commiſs' ſuit per
Warrantum Dominorum de <pb n="87" facs="tcp:116495:45"/> Privat' Concilio cujus tenor
ſequitur in haec verba. viz.</hi> To the Keeper of the <hi>Gatehouſe,
&amp;c. vide</hi> Maſter <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> preſidents; but ſee upon what
ground he was bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, it was a ſpeciall command of the Lords of the
Councell. <hi>Vide</hi> the Record.</p>
               <p>Theſe are all the Records and preſidents that you mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred
unto us in your Argument, and that were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto us, for I have dealt
faithfully with you, and now you have ſeen them in the Caſes, I would have
any man judge of the concluſion which you made the laſt day, That when a
man is committed, and the caſe not known, but it is certified to be by the
Kings ſpeciall commandment, and the <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> is procured by
your ſelves and ſpeeded by the King, that we can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge or bail
them.</p>
               <p>Then the preſidents are all againſt you every one of them, and
what ſhall guide our judgements, ſince there is nothing alledged in this
caſe but preſidents? that if no cauſe of the commitment be expreſſed,
it is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to be for matter of State, which we cannot take notice
of; you ſee we finde none, no not one, that hath been delivered by bail in
the like caſes, but by the hand of the King or his direction.</p>
               <p>If we ſhould ceaſe here, you ſee you have ſhewn no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
to ſatisfie us, and we know that you that be of their Councell, will
ſatisfie your Clients therein.</p>
               <p>But you ſhall ſee that we have taken a little pains in this
Caſe, and we will ſhew you ſome preſidents on the other ſide; and I
beleeve there be five hundreth of this nature that may be cited to this
purpoſe, I ſhall go retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade and go backwards in citing the years of the
preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents that I ſhall mention.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:116495:46"/> I will begin with 7 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Edward
Page,</hi> he was brought hither by the Steward of the
<hi>Marſhalſeys,</hi> who returned that he was committed <hi>Per mandatum
domini Regis,</hi> and he was remitted, ſo that he was not delivered upon
this generall Return, but he was remaunded.</p>
               <p>The next was 12 <hi>H.</hi> 7. there you ſhall ſee a
preſident where one was committed, his name was <hi>Thomas Yow,</hi> he was
committed for felony, and alſo <hi>Per mandatum domini Regis,</hi> and the
Kings Atturney came hither and releaſed the Kings command, and thereupon he
was bailed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Maſter <hi>Noye.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>It is all one with <hi>Parkers</hi> Caſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chief Iuſtice <hi>Hide.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>No, for here were two cauſes of the commitment, <hi>Hubbert</hi>
was then the Kings Atturney, and he ſignified in open Court that he was
diſcharged by the Kings command, and <hi>Poſtea traditur in ball' pro
ſuſpicione fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next was <hi>Humphrey Booths,</hi> 9 <hi>H.</hi> 7.
<hi>Rot.</hi> 14. you ſhall finde it much to that purpoſe as the other was
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; he was impriſoned for an outlawry, and by the commandment of the
King alſo, and after that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe of the Kings commandment was
certified to the chief Juſtice, he was thereupon diſcharged. <hi>Vide</hi>
the Record.</p>
               <p>The next is 7 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Thomas Brown, Iohn Rawlings,</hi>
and <hi>Robert Sherman</hi> and others, were committed <hi>Per man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum domini
Regis,</hi> and for felony, outlawry, and other cauſes, as appears by the
Records, and after the King releaſeth his commandment, and that the outlawry
ſhould be reverſed, and for the felony he was bailed. <hi>Vide</hi> the
Record.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:116495:46"/> So that you may ſee the offences mentioned
in the Warrant for the commitment were triable here, and when the King
releaſes his commandment they were bailed for the reſt, but they that were
committed by the commandment of the King were releaſed by the King.</p>
               <p>In 7 <hi>H.</hi> 7. the Caſes of <hi>William Bartholmew, Henry
Carre,</hi> and others, is to the ſame effect, by all which you may ſee,
that when the King releaſeth his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they were bailed for the
reſt, and as they were committed by the Kings commandment, ſo they were
releaſed by the Kings command.</p>
               <p>Now here I ſhall trouble you with no more preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and you
ſee your own what concluſion they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce. And thoſe ſtrong
preſidents alledged on the other ſide, we are not wiſer then they that
went before us; and the common cuſtome of the Law is, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of the
Land, and that hath been the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all common cuſtome of the Law, to which
we are to ſubmit, for we come not to charge the Law, but to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to
it.</p>
               <p>We have looked upon that preſident that was men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by
Maſter Atturney. The reſolution of all the Judges of <hi>England</hi> in 34
<hi>Eliz.</hi> we have conſidered of the time, and I think there were not
before, nor have been ſince more upright Judges then they were, <hi>Wray</hi>
was one, and <hi>Anderſon</hi> another: In <hi>Eaſter</hi> Term this was
certified under the hands of all the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> and Barons of
the Exchequer in a duplicate, whereof the one was delivered to the Lord
Chancellor, and the other to the Lord Treaſurer, to be delivered to the
Queen. We have compared our copies, not taking them the one from the other, but
bringing them: we have long had <pb n="90" facs="tcp:116495:47"/> them by us together, and
they all agree word for word, and that which M. Atturney ſaid, he had out of
Judge <hi>Anderſons</hi> Book, and it is to this purpoſe, to omit other
things, That if a man be committed by the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King, he is not
to be delivered by a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> in this Court, for we know not the
cauſe of the commitment. <hi>Vide</hi> this at the latter end of the firſt
part of Maſter <hi>Seldens</hi> Argument as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>But the Queſtion now is, Whether we may deliver this Gentleman
or not, you ſee what hath been the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in all the Kings times
heretofore, and your own Records, and this reſolution of all the Judges
teacheth us, and what can we do but walk in the ſteps of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers? If
you ask me which way you ſhould be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, we ſhall tell you, we muſt
not counſell you.</p>
               <p>Maſter Atturney hath told you that the King hath done it, and we
truſt him in great matters, and he is bound by Law, and he bids us proceed by
Law, as we are ſworn to do, and ſo is the King; and we make no doubt but
the King if you ſeek to him, he knowing the cauſe why you are impriſoned,
he will have mercy, but we leave that. If in Juſtice we ought to deliver you
we would do it, but upon theſe grounds, and theſe Records, and the
preſidents and reſolutions we cannot deliver you, but you muſt be
remanded. Now if I have miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken any thing, I deſire to be righted by my
brethren, I have indeavoured to give the reſolutions of us all.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:116495:47"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTY: The humble Petition of Sir
<hi>John Elliot</hi> Knight, Priſoner in the Gatehouſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the
LOANE.<note place="margin">Delivered the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb.</hi> 1627. but
never an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note>
            </head>
            <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT your poore ſuppliant affected with ſorrow and
unhappineſſe, through the long senſe of your Majeſties diſpleaſure,
willing in every act of duty and obedience to ſatisfie your Majeſty of the
loyalty of his heart, then which he hath nothing more deſired, that there may
not remain a jealouſie in your roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all breaſt, that ſtubbornneſſe and
will have been the motives of his forbearing to condeſcend to the ſaid
Loan, low as your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe foot, with a ſad yet a faithfull heart, for
an Apology to your Clemency and Grace, he now preſumes to offer up the
Reaſons <pb n="92" facs="tcp:116495:48"/> that induced him, which he conceiveth
neceſſity of his duty to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion Juſtice, and your Majeſty did
inforce.</p>
            <p>The Rule of Juſtice he takes to be the Law, impartiall Arbiter
of Governments and obedience, the ſupport and ſtrength of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, the
obſervation of that Juſtice by which ſubjection is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, Religion
(adding to theſe power not to be reſiſted) binde up the conſcience in
an Obligation to that rule which (without open prejudice and violence of
theſe duties) may not be impeached.</p>
            <p>In this particular therefore for the Loan, being deſirous to be
ſatisfied how farre the Obligation might extend, and reſolving where he was
left maſter of his own, to become ſervant to your will, he had recourſe
unto the Laws, to be informed by them; which in all humility he ſubmitteth to
your moſt ſacred view in the Collections following.</p>
            <p>In the time of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. he findeth that the Commons of
that age were ſo tender of their Liberties, as they feared even their own
free Acts and gifts might turn them to a Bondage and their heires, wherefore it
was deſired and granted:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">25 E. 1.</note>That for no buſineſſe
ſuch manner of Aids, Taxes, nor Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes ſhould be taken but by common
aſſent of the Realm, and for the common Profit thereof.</p>
            <p>The like was in force by the ſame King, and by two other Laws
again enacted:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Stat. Tallage. &amp; 33 E. 1.</note>That no
Tallage or Aid ſhould be taken or levied without the good will and aſſent
of the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Earls, Barons Knights, Burgeſſes, and
other Freemen of the Land.</p>
            <p>And that prudent and magnanimous Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the third;
led by the ſame Wiſdome, having granted:</p>
            <p>That the greateſt gift given in Parliament for the aid and
ſpeed of his matchleſſe undertaking againſt <hi>France,</hi> ſhould
not be <pb n="93" facs="tcp:116495:48"/> had in example, nor fall to the prejudice of the
Subject in time to come; did likewiſe adde in confirmation of that Right,
That they ſhould not from thenceforth be grieved to ſuſtain any charge or
aid but by the common aſſent, and that in Parliament.</p>
            <p>And more particularly upon this point, upon a Petition of the
Commons afterwards in Parliament it was eſtabliſhed:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rot. 16. 25 E. 3.</note>That the Loans which
are granted to the King by divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, be releaſed, and that none from
henceforth be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to make ſuch Loans againſt their wills, becauſe
it is againſt reaſon and the Franchiſes of the Land, and reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
be made to ſuch as made ſuch Loans.</p>
            <p>And by another Act upon a new occaſion, in the time of
<hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the third it was ordained:</p>
            <p>That the Subject in no wiſe be charged with any ſuch charge,
exaction, or impoſition called a Benevolence, nor ſuch like Charge, and
that ſuch like exactions be damned and annul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 R. 3.</note>Such were the opinions of theſe
times, for all theſe Aids, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volences, Loans, and ſuch like charges
exacted from the Subject not in Parliament, which they held to be grievances
contrary to their Liberties, and illegall: And ſo pious were their Princes in
confirmation of their Liberties, as having ſecured them for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by
ſuch frequent Laws and Statutes, they did likewiſe by them provide for
their poſterity; and in ſome ſo ſtrictly that they bound the
obſervation with a curſe: as in that of 33 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. and alſo
under pain of excommunication, as by the other of the 25 of the ſame King,
which was to be denounced againſt all thoſe that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late or break them,
which Act extends to us.</p>
            <p>And theſe reaſons he preſents to your moſt ſacred
Majeſty as the firſt motive taken from the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:116495:49"/> There are others alſo, which in his humble
apprehenſion he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Action it ſelf, which he likewiſe
tenders to your moſt excellent Wiſdome.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>1</label> Firſt, that the carriage and
inſtructions accompanied with the Authority of the great Seal imported a
conſtraint, ſuch requeſts to Subjects being tacite and implied commands,
and ſo preventing that readineſſe and love which in a free way would have
farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thoſe demands, whereas the wonted Aids given to your happy
Anceſtors were <hi>ex ſpontanea voluntate &amp; charitate po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli,</hi>
whereby they made that conjunction of their hearts at home which wrought ſuch
power and reputation to their Acts abroad.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>2</label> Whereas the firmeſt obligation of
that readineſſe and love is the benignity of Princes, giving and
preſerving to their people juſt and decent Liberties, which to this
Kingdome are derived from the Clemency and Wiſdome of your Progenitors, to
whom there is owing a ſacred memory for them: he could not as he feared
without preſſure to theſe immunities, become an actor in this Loan, which
by impriſonment and reſtraint was urged, contrary to the Graunts of the
great Charter, by ſo many glorious and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Kings, ſo many times
confirmed, being therein moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of your Majeſty that never King
that raigned over us, had of his own benignity and goodneſſe a more pious
diſpoſition to preſerve the juſt liberties of his Subjects then your
ſacred ſelf.<note place="margin">Chart. Libert. 9 H. 5. confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med 25 E. 1.
1, 4, 5, 10, 14, 28, 31, 36, 42, 45, 50 E. 3. 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 9, 13 H. 4. 4 H.
5. 2 H. 6. &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>3</label> Though we were well aſſured by
your Majeſties Royall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, whoſe words he holds as Oracles of truth,
that it ſhould not become a preſident during the happineſſe of your
Raign, the long continuance whereof is the daily ſubject of his prayers yet
he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from thence a fear, that ſucceeding ages might thereby take
occaſion for poſterity to ſtrike at the propriety of their goods,
contrary to the piety and intention of your Majeſty ſo graciouſly
expreſt.</p>
            <p>And theſe being the true grounds and motives of his forbearance
to the ſaid Loan, ſhewing ſuch inconveniences in reaſon, and
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting it an Act contradicting ſo many of your Laws, and 
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:116495:49"/> moſt of them by the moſt prudent and happy of our
Princes gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which could not, without preſumption, beyond pardon in your
ſuppliant, in taking to himſelf the diſpenſation of thoſe Laws, ſo
piouſly enacted, by him violated or impeached.</p>
            <p>In the fulneſſe of all ſubmiſſion and obedience, as the
Apology of his loyalty and duty, he lowly offers to your moſt ſacred
Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for the ſatisfaction of your Majeſty, moſt humbly praying your
Majeſty will be graciouſly pleaſed to take them into your Princely
conſideration, where when it ſhall appear (as he doubts not but from hence
it will to your deep judgement) that no facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humour nor diſaffection led
on by ſtubbornneſſe and will hath herein ſtirred or moved him, but the
juſt obligation of his conſcience, which binds him to the ſervice of your
Majeſty, in the obſervance of your Laws, he is hopefull (preſuming upon
the Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Juſtice of your Majeſty) that your Majeſty, according to
your innate Clemency and Goodneſſe, will be pleaſed to reſtore him to
your favour and his liberty, and to afford him the benefit of thoſe Laws
which in all humility he craves.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
